<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<!-- <appendix xml:id="appendix-c"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>References</title> -->
<references xml:id="bibliography" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Bibliography</title>

	<biblio type="raw">Ahrens, C. Donald. <title>Essentials of Meteorology</title>. Belmont, CA: Wadsworth, 1998.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Alexander, R. M. <title>The Human Machine</title>. Natural History Museum Publications, 1992.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Altenburg, Edgar. <title>Genetics</title>. New York: Holt Rinehart and Winston, 1956.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Atkins, P. W. and Beran, J. A. <title>General Chemistry</title>. Scientific American Books, 1989.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Baddeley, Alan D. <title>Essentials of Human Memory</title>. Psychology Press Ltd., 1999.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Belovsky, G. E. "Diet Optimization in a Generalist Herbivore: The Moose." <journal>Theoretical Population Biology</journal>, 14 (1978), 105–134.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Belovsky, G. E. "Generalist Herbivore Foraging and Its Role in Competitive Interactions." <journal>American Zoologist</journal>, 26 (1986), 51–69.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Bender, Edward. <title>An Introduction to Mathematical Modeling</title>. Mineola, NY: Dover Publications, 1978.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Berg, Richard and Stork, David. <title>The Physics of Sound</title>. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1982.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Boleman, Jay. <title>Physics, a Window on Our World</title>. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1982.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Bolton, William. <title>Patterns in Physics</title>. McGraw Hill, 1974.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Brandt, John C. and Maran, Stephen P. <title>New Horizons in Astronomy</title>. San Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1972.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Briggs, David and Courtney, Frank. <title>Agriculture and Environment</title>. Singapore: Longman Scientific and Technical, 1985.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Burton, R. F. <title>Biology by Numbers</title> . Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Carr, Bernard, and Giddings. Steven. "Quantum Black Holes."" <journal>Scientific American</journal>, May 2005.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Chapman J. L. and Reiss M. J. <title>Ecology: Principles and Applications</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1992.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Davis, Kimmet, and Autry. <title>Physical Education: Theory and Practice</title>. Macmillan Education Australia PTY Ltd., 1986.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Deffeyes, Kenneth. <title>Hubbert's Peak</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2001.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw"><title>The Earth and Its Place in the Universe</title>. Open University, Milton Keynes, 1998.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Fowler, Murray and Miller, Eric. <title>Zoo and Wild Animal Medicine</title>. Saunders, 1999.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Gillner, Thomas C. <title>Modern Ship Design</title>. U.S. Naval Institute Press, 1972.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw"><title>The Guiness Book of Records</title>, 1998. Guinness Publishing Ltd., 1997.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Hayward, Geoff. <title>Applied Ecology</title>. Thomas Nelson and Sons, Ltd., 1992.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Holme, David J., and Peck, Hazel. <title>Analytical Biochemistry</title>. Longman Scientific and Technical, 1993.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Hunt, J. A. and Sykes, A. <title>Chemistry</title>. Longman Group Ltd., 1984.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Hutson, A. H. <title>The Pocket Guide to Mammals of Britain and Europe</title>. Dragon’s World Ltd., 1995.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Ingham, Neil. <title>Astrophysics</title>. International Thomson Publishing, 1997.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Karttunen, H. et al. <title>Fundamental Astronomy</title>. Springer-Verlag, 1987.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Krebs J. R. and Davies N. B. <title>An Introduction to Behavioural Ecology</title>. Oxford: Blackwell Scientific Publications, 1993.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Leopold, Luna B., Wolman, M. Gordon, and Miller, John P. <title>Fluvial Processes in Geomorphology</title>. New York: Dover Publications, Inc., 1992.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Mannering, Fred, and Kilareski, Walter. <title>Principles of Highway Engineering and Traffic Analysis</title>. New York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1998.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Meadows, Donella, Randers, Jorgen, and Meadows, Dennis. <title>Limits to Growth, the 30-Year Update</title>. White River Junction, VT: Chelsea Green Publishing Co., 2004.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Mee, Frederick. <title>Sound</title>. Heinemann Educational Books, 1967.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Oglesby, Clarkson and Hicks, R. Gary. <title>Highway Engineering</title>. New York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1982.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Oliver, C. P. "The Effect of Varying the Duration of X-Ray Treatment upon the Frequency of Mutation," <journal>Science</journal>, 71 (1930), 44–46. </biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Perrins, C. M. <title>British Tits</title>. Collins, London, 1979.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Perrins, C. M. and Moss, D. "Reproductive Rates in the Great Tit." <journal>Journal of Animal Ecology</journal>, 44 (1975), 695–706.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Plummer, David. <title>Biochemistry, the Chemistry of Life</title>. London: McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1989.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Pope, Jean A. <title>Medical Physics</title>. Heinemann Educational, 1989.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">P. E. di Prampero et al. <journal>Journal of Applied Physiology</journal>, 37 (1974), 1–5.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Pratt, Paul W. <title>Principles and Practices of Veterinary Technology</title>. Mosby, 1998.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Pugh, L. G. C. E. "Relation of Oxygen Intake and Speed in Competition Cycling and Comparative Observations on the Bicycle Ergometer." <journal>Journal of Physiology</journal>, 241 (1974), 795–808</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Scarf, Philip. "An Empirical Basis for Naismith’s Rule." <journal>Mathematics Today</journal>, vol. 34 no. 5 (1998), 149–151</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Schad, Jerry. <title>Afoot and Afield in Los Angeles County</title>. Berkeley: Wilderness Press, 1991.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut. <title>How Animals Work</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1972.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Schmidt-Nielsen, Knut. <title>Scaling: Why Is Animal Size so Important?</title> Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1984.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Sears, Francis. <title>Mechanics, Heat, and Sound</title>. Sternberg, Robert J. In Search of the Human Mind. Harcourt Brace College Publishing, 1995.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Storch, Hammon, and Bunch. <title>Ship Production</title>. Cornell Maritime Press, 1988.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Strickberger, Monroe W. <title>Genetics</title>. Macmillan, 1976.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Underwood, Benton J. "Forgetting." <journal>Scientific American</journal>, vol. 210, no. 3, 91–99.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Weisberg, Joseph and Parish, Howard. <title>Introductory Oceanography</title>. McGraw-Hill, 1974.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Wilkinson, G. S. "Reciprocal Food Sharing in the Vampire Bat". <journal>Nature</journal>, 308 (1984), 181–184.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Wood, Alexander. <title>The Physics of Music</title>. Chapman and Hall, 1975.</biblio>

	<biblio type="raw">Wright, Paul and Paquette, Radnor. <title>Highway Engineering</title>. New York: John Wiley and Sons, Inc., 1987.</biblio>
</references>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->