<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->
    <chapter xml:id="chap1"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
        <title>Triangles and Circles</title>
<introduction>
<sidebyside widths="60% 40%" valigns="middle middle"><p>
<ul>
	<li><m>\blert{\textbf{Angles and Triangles}}</m></li>
	<li><m>\blert{\textbf{Similar Triangles}}</m></li>
	<li><m>\blert{\textbf{Circles}}</m></li></ul></p>
<image source="images/ch1-1.png"><description>design</description></image></sidebyside>        
  
 <p>Circles and triangles are the simplest geometric figures. A circle is the simplest sort of curve, and a triangle is the simplest polygon -- the one with the fewest sides. Each has properties that makes it useful in many fields of endeavor.  A triangle is the most stable of polygons, because once its sides are fixed in length, its angles cannot change. A triangular truss bridge is a stable structure. A three-legged stool will not wobble.</p>
 
 <sidebyside widths="50% 50%"><image source="images/ch1-2.png"><description>bridge</description></image><image source="images/ch1-3.png"><description>dome</description></image></sidebyside> 

 <p>A circle encloses more area then any other figure of the same length, or perimeter, and a sphere encloses more space. A geodesic dome is a portion of a sphere constructed with triangles.  It has been called "the strongest, lightest and most efficient means of enclosing space known to man.”</p>
<p>Geodesic domes may also help us learn how to live on another planet. In 2017, the United Arab Emirates began construction on Mars Science City, a series of interconnecting geodesic domes designed to be a realistic model for living on Mars. The city will cover 1.9 million square feet, and its walls will be 3D-printed using sand from the desert.</p>
 
 <sidebyside width="70%"><image source="images/ch1-4.png"><description>dome</description></image></sidebyside>  

 <p>The city will contain laboratories to address food, sustainability, and energy issues all over the world. Finally, the project will implement an experiment wherein a team will spend a year living in the simulated planet for a year.</p> 

 <sidebyside width="70%"><image source="images/ch1-5.png"><description>dome</description></image></sidebyside>  


 <activity><title>Properties of Triangles</title>
<p></p>
<p>Materials:  You will need paper and pencil, scissors, a ruler and compass, and two plastic straws.</p>
<p>Prepare:  Cut the straw into pieces of lengths 2 inches, 3 inches, and 6 inches. Use the ruler to draw a large triangle, and cut it out.</p>
<p><ol label="A">
<li><p>What do we know about the sides of a triangle?</p>
	<p><ol label="1">
	<li><p><ol label="a">
		<li>Can you make a triangle with sides of length 2 inches, 3 inches, and 6 inches?</li>
		<li>Use the pieces of length 2 inches and 3 inches to form two sides of a triangle. What 
		happens to the length of the third side as you increase the angle between the first two 
		sides?</li>
		<li>What is the longest that the third side could be? What is the smallest?</li></ol></p></li>
	<li>Two sides of a triangle are 6 centimeters and 8 centimeters long. What are the possible 
	lengths of the third side?</li>
	<li>Two sides of a triangle are <m>p</m> units and <m>q</m> units long. What are the possible lengths of the 
	third side?</li></ol></p></li>
<li><p>What do we know about the angles of a triangle?</p>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>Use a protractor to measure the three angles of the paper triangle in degrees. Now add up the three angles. What is their sum?</li>
	<li>Tear off the three corners of the triangle. Place them side-by-side with their vertices (tips) at the same point. What do you find?</li>  
	<li>How are your answers to parts (1) and (2) related?</li></ol></p></li>
<li><p>How are the sides and angles of a triangle related?</p>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>A standard way to label a triangle is to call the angles <m>A,~B,</m> and <m>C</m>. The side opposite angle <m>A</m> is called <m>a</m>, the side opposite angle <m>B</m> is called <m>b</m>, and the side opposite angle <m>C</m> is called <m>c</m>. Sketch a triangle and label it with standard notation.</li>
	<li>Using a ruler, carefully draw a triangle and label it with standard notation so that <m>a \gt b \gt c</m>. Now use a protractor to measure the angles and list them in order from largest to smallest. What do you observe?</li>
	<li>Using a ruler, carefully draw another triangle and label it with standard notation so that <m>A \gt B \gt C</m>. Now use a ruler to measure the sides and list them in order from largest to smallest. What do you observe?</li></ol></p></li>
<li><p>What do we know about right triangles?</p>
<p><ol label="1">
	<li>The side opposite the <m>90\degree</m> angle in a right triangle is called the <term>hypotenuse</term>. Why is the hypotenuse always the longest side of a right triangle?</li>
	<li><p>The Pythagorean theorem states that:

		<me>\text{IF}:~~ 	a,~b,~ \text{and}~c~ \text{are the sides of a right triangle, and}~c~ \text{is the hypotenuse,}</me>
		<me>\text{THEN}:~~a^2 + b^2 = c^2~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~</me>		
	The "if" part of the theorem is called the <term>hypothesis</term>, and the "then" part is called the <term>conclusion</term>.  The <term>converse</term> of a theorem is the new statement you obtain when you interchange the hypothesis and the conclusion.  Write the converse of the Pythagorean theorem.</p></li>
	<li><p>The converse of the Pythagorean theorem is also true. Use the converse to decide whether each of the following triangles is a right triangle. Support your conclusions with calculations.
		<p><ol label="a" cols = "2">
			<li><m>a = 9,~ b = 16,~ c = 25</m></li>
			<li><m>a = 12,~ b = 16,~ c = 20</m></li>
			<li><m>a = \sqrt{8},~ b = \sqrt{5},~ c = \sqrt{13}</m></li>
			<li><m>a = \dfrac{\sqrt{3}}{2},~ b = \dfrac{1}{2},~ c = 1</m></li></ol></p></p></li>
	</ol></p></li>
</ol></p>
	
	


	












</activity>
 </introduction>

    <xi:include href="./section-1-1.xml" />             
    <xi:include href="./section-1-2.xml" />            
    <xi:include href="./section-1-3.xml" />                     
        <xi:include href="./chap1-summary.xml" />      
        
</chapter>
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->