<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="chap1-summary" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Chapter 1 Summary and Review</title>

<subsection><title>Key Concepts</title>

<p><ol label="1">
	<li>The sum of the angles in a triangle is <m>180\degree</m>.</li>
	<li>A right triangle has one angle of <m>90\degree</m>.</li>
	<li>All of the angles of an equilateral triangle are equal.</li>
	<li>The base angles of an isosceles triangle are equal.</li>
	<li>Vertical angles are equal.</li>
	<li>If parallel lines are intersected by a transversal, the alternate interior angles are equal.  Corresponding angles are also equal.</li>
	<li>Two triangles are <term>congruent</term> if they have exactly the same size and shape.</li>
	<li>The <term>altitude</term> of an equilateral triangle divides it into two congruent right triangles.</li>
	<li>In a <m>30\degree-60\degree-90\degree</m> right triangle, the leg opposite the <m>30\degree</m> angle is half the length of the hypotenuse.</li>
	<li>Two triangles are <term>similar</term> if they have the same shape but not necessarily the same size.  The corresponding angles are equal, and the corresponding sides are <term>proportional</term>.</li>
	<li><assemblage><title>Similar Triangles</title>
        <p>Two triangles are similar if either
            <ol label="1">
                <li> their corresponding angles are equal, or</li>
                <li> their corresponding sides are proportional.</li>
                </ol> </p></assemblage></li>
     <li>If two <em>right</em> triangles have <em>one</em> pair of corresponding acute angles with the same measure, then the triangles are similar.</li>
     <li><assemblage><title>Distance Formula</title>
		<p>The distance <m>d</m> between two points <m>P_{1}(x_1, y_1)</m> and <m>P_{2}(x_2, y_2)</m> is
		<me>d=\sqrt{(x_2-x_1)^2+(y_2-y_1)^2}</me></p></assemblage></li>
	<li>Any number that can be written as a quotient of two integers <m>\dfrac{a}{b},~~ b\not=0,~~</m>,  is called a <term>rational number</term>.  The decimal form of a rational number is either a <term>terminating decimal</term> or a <term>repeating decimal</term>.</li>  
	<li>An <term>irrational number</term> is one that cannot be written as a quotient of two integers <m>\dfrac{a}{b},~~ b\not=0,~~</m>.  We cannot write down an exact decimal equivalent for an irrational number.</li>
	<li>A <term>circle</term> is the set of all points in a plane that lie at a given distance, called the <term>radius</term>, from a fixed point called the <term>center</term>.</li>
	<li><assemblage><title>Circle</title>
		<p>The equation for a <term>circle</term> of radius <m>r</m> centered at the origin is
		<me>x^2+y^2=r^2</me></p></assemblage></li>
	<li>The circle <m>x^2 + y^2 = 1</m>, which is centered at the origin and has radius 1 unit, is called the <term>unit circle</term>.</li>
	<li><assemblage><title>Circumference of a Circle</title>
		<p>The <term>circumference</term> of a circle of radius <m>r</m> is given by
		<me>C=2\pi r</me></p></assemblage></li>
	<li><assemblage><title>Area of a Circle</title>
		<p>The <term>area</term> of a circle of radius <m>r</m> is given by
		<me>A=\pi r^2</me></p></assemblage></li> 
	</ol></p>
</subsection>
<!-- <subsubsection> -->
	<xi:include href="./chap1-rev-problems.xml" /> <!-- exercises  -->
<!-- </subsubsection> -->

</section>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->