<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2016 Katherine Yoshiwara












You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with MathBook XML.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
*********************************************************************-->
<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!-- (as copied on 2016/28/04)                     -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Modeling, Functions, and Graphs   -->
<!--           4th                                     -->
<!-- Copyright (C) Katherine Yoshiwara      -->

<frontmatter xml:id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <titlepage>
        <author>
            <personname>Katherine Yoshiwara</personname>
            <department>Department of Mathematics</department>
            <institution>Los Angeles Pierce College</institution>
<!--            <email>kyoshiwara@hotmail.com</email>  -->
        </author>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>

    <colophon>
        <copyright>
            <year>2016<ndash />2017</year>
            <holder>Katherine Yoshiwara</holder>
            <minilicense>GFDL License</minilicense>
            <shortlicense>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  A copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled <q>GNU Free Documentation License.</q>  All trademarks<trademark /> are the registered<registered /> marks of their respective owners.</shortlicense>
        </copyright>
    </colophon>

    <!-- A section of its own in HTML, migrates to copyright-page in LaTeX (sans a title)-->
    <biography>
        <p>
            Katherine Yoshiwara did her undergraduate work at Michigan State and her graduate work at UCLA. She has received teaching awards from the Mathematical Association of America,  the American Mathematical Association of Two-Year Colleges, and the National Institute of Staff and Organizational Development.
        </p>
        <p>
            She retired from Los Angeles Pierce College, is learning to play the cello, and likes gardening.</p>
    </biography>

    <!-- The following items must be placed in the desired/required order -->
    <!-- This will be checked by a Document Type Definition eventually -->
    <!-- Order: dedication, acknowledgements, forewords, prefaces -->

    <!-- Each paragraph gets centered and has some vertical separatation -->
    <!-- A line break may be used here to aid with intended formatting   -->
    <!--  <dedication> -->
    <!--    <p>To students of algebra everywhere<ndash />they are the reason</p> -->
    <!--   <p>And to those who teach them</p>  -->
    <!-- </dedication> -->

    <acknowledgement>
        <p>I would like to thank my cats.</p>
        <p>I would also like to acknowledge Bruce Yoshiwara for  helpful comments and suggestions. </p>
    </acknowledgement>

    <preface>
    <p>Mathematics, as we all know, is the language of science, and fluency in algebraic skills has always been necessary for anyone aspiring to disciplines based on calculus. But in the information age, increasingly sophisticated mathematical methods are used in all fields of knowledge, from archaeology to zoology. Consequently, there is a new focus on the courses before calculus. The availability of calculators and computers allows students to tackle complex problems involving real data, but requires more attention to analysis and interpretation of results. All students, not just those headed for science and engineering, should develop a mathematical viewpoint, including critical thinking, problem-solving strategies, and estimation, in addition to computational skills. <em>Modeling, Functions and Graphs</em> employs a variety of applications to motivate mathematical thinking.</p>

<sidebyside><paragraphs><title>Modeling</title>
    <p>The ability to model problems or phenomena by algebraic expressions and equations is the ultimate goal of any algebra course. Through a variety of applications, we motivate students to develop the skills and techniques of algebra. Each chapter includes an interactive Investigation that gives students an opportunity to explore an openended modeling problem. These Investigations can be used in class as guided explorations or as projects for small groups. They are designed to show students how the mathematical techniques they are learning can be applied to study and understand new situations.</p></paragraphs></sidebyside>

<sidebyside><paragraphs><title>Functions</title>
<p>The fundamental concept underlying calculus and related disciplines is the notion of function, and students should acquire a good understanding of functions before they embark on their study of college-level mathematics. While the formal study of functions is usually the content of precalculus, it is not too early to begin building an intuitive understanding of functional relationships in the preceding algebra courses. These ideas are useful not only in calculus but in practically any field students may pursue. We begin working with functions in Chapter 1 and explore the different families of functions in subsequent chapters.</p>
<p>In all our work with functions and modeling we employ the "Rule of Four,"" that all
problems should be considered using algebraic, numerical, graphical, and verbal methods.
It is the connections between these approaches that we have endeavored to establish in this course. At this level it is crucial that students learn to write an algebraic expression from a verbal description, recognize trends in a table of data, and
extract and interpret information from the graph of a function.</p></paragraphs></sidebyside>

<sidebyside><paragraphs><title>Graphs</title>
<p>No tool for conveying information about a system is more powerful than a graph. Yet many students have trouble progressing from a point-wise understanding of graphs to a more
global view. By taking advantage of graphing calculators, we examine a large number of examples and study them in more detail than is possible when every graph is plotted by hand. We can consider more realistic models in which calculations by more traditional methods are difficult or impossible.</p>
<p>We have incorporated graphing calculators into the text wherever they can be used to enhance understanding. Calculator use is not simply an add-on, but in many ways shapes
the organization of the material. The text includes instructions for the TI-84 graphing calculator, but these can easily be adapted to any other graphing utility. We have not attempted to use all the features of the calculator or to teach calculator use for its own sake, but in all cases have let the mathematics suggest how technology should be used.</p></paragraphs></sidebyside>
<p></p>

        <!-- RAB 2014/08/18 Should move flush right with some vertical spacing -->
        <attribution><line>Katherine Yoshiwara</line> <line>Atascadero, CA 2016</line></attribution>

    </preface>

    <preface>
        <title>Contributors to the 5<m>^\mathrm{th}</m> Edition</title>

        <contributors>
            <contributor xml:id="kyoshiwara">
                <personname>Katherine Yoshiwara</personname>
                <department>Emerita Professor of Mathematics</department>
                <institution>Los Angeles Pierce College</institution>
<!--                <email>yoshiwka@piercecollege.edu</email> -->
            </contributor>
            <contributor xml:id="bkyoshiwara">
                <personname>Bruce Yoshiwara</personname>
                <department>Emeritus Professor of Mathematics</department>
                <institution>Los Angeles Pierce College</institution>
                <email>byoshiwara@gmail.com</email>
            </contributor>
      </contributors>

    </preface>

</frontmatter>