<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="The-Law-of-Sines"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>The Law of Sines</title><introduction>
<p>
We have learned to use the trigonometric ratios to solve right triangles. But the trig ratios are only valid for the sides of right triangles. Can we find unknown sides or angles in an oblique triangle?</p> 

<sidebyside width="70%" > <image source="images/3-2-intro.png"><description>triangles</description></image></sidebyside> 

<p>In this section we find relationships among the sides and angles of oblique triangles. These relationships are called the Law of Sines and the Law of Cosines. To derive these new rules, we use what we already know about right triangles.</p> 

<note><p>Reducing a new problem to an earlier one is a frequently used technique in mathematics.</p></note>

<sidebyside widths="50% 45%"><p>Consider the oblique triangle at right.  By drawing in the altitude <m>h</m> of the triangle, we create two right triangles, <m>\triangle BCD</m> and <m>\triangle ABD</m>, as shown in the figure. Now we can write expressions in terms of <m>h</m> for <m>\sin A</m> and for <m>\sin C</m>.</p> <image source="images/3-2-tworight.png"><description>triangles</description></image></sidebyside>

<p>Looking at <m>\triangle BCD</m>, we see that <m>\dfrac{h}{a} = \sin C.</m></p>
<p>  Looking at <m>\triangle ABD</m>, we see that <m>\dfrac{h}{c} = \sin A.</m> </p>
<p> Now we solve each of these equations for <m>h</m>: 

\begin{align*}
                \dfrac{h}{a} \amp = \sin C ~~~~~~~~    \dfrac{h}{c} = \sin A\amp\amp \text{Solve each equation for } h.\\
                h \amp = a \sin C~~~~~~    h = c \sin A \amp\amp \text{Equate the expressions for } h.\\
                \end{align*} 
 \begin{align*}               
                a \sin C \amp = c \sin A  \amp\amp \text{Divide both sides by } ac.\\
                \dfrac {\sin C}{c} \amp = \dfrac {\sin A}{a} \\            
                \end{align*}

<p> We have derived a relationship between the angles <m>A</m> and <m>C</m> and their opposite sides, <m>a</m> and <m>c</m>. If we know any three of these quantities, we can find the fourth.</p>  
<p>In a similar way, by drawing in the altitude from the vertex <m>C</m>, we can show that <me>\dfrac {\sin A}{a} = \dfrac {\sin B}{b}</me>. Putting both results together, we have the Law of Sines. The Law of Sines is true for any triangle, whether it is acute, right, or obtuse.</p>

<assemblage><title>Law of Sines</title>
<p>If the angles of a triangle are <m>A, B</m>, and <m>C</m>, and the opposite sides are respectively <m>a, b,</m> and <m>c</m>, then</p>
<sidebyside widths="60% 30%"><p><me>\dfrac {\sin A}{a} = \dfrac {\sin B}{b} = \dfrac {\sin C}{c}</me></p> <image source="images/3-2-sineslaw.png"><description>triangle</description></image></sidebyside>
<p>or equivalently, <me>\dfrac {a}{\sin A} = \dfrac {b}{\sin B} = \dfrac {c}{\sin C}</me></p>         
</assemblage>
</introduction>

<subsection><title>Finding a Side</title>
<p> So far, we have only been able to find unknown sides in right triangles. We can use the Law of Sines in oblique triangles as well. In the next example, we use the Law of Sines to find a distance.</p>

    

</subsection>
<!--<xi:include href="./summary-3-2.xml" /> 
<xi:include href="./section-3-2-exercises.xml" /> --> <!-- exercises  -->

</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->