<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="SimTri"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Similar Triangles</title>

<subsection><title>Congruent Triangles</title>   
<p>
    Two triangles are <term>congruent</term> if they have exactly the same size and shape.  This means that their corresponding angles are equal, and their corresponding sides have the same lengths, as shown below.
</p>
<sidebyside width="100%"><image source="images/congtri.png"><description>congruent triangles</description></image> </sidebyside>


<example><statement>
    <p>The two triangles below are congruent.  List the corresponding parts, and find the angles <m>\theta</m>, <m>\phi</m>, and <m>\chi</m>, and side <m>z</m>.</p>
    <sidebyside width="60%"> <image source="images/exam1-2-1.png"><description>cong triangles w vert angles</description></image></sidebyside>
</statement>
<solution><p> In these triangles, <m>\angle B=\angle D</m> because they are both right angles, and <m>\angle BCA=\angle DCE</m>  because they are vertical angles, so <m>\theta =25\degree</m>. The third angles, <m>\angle A</m> and <m>\angle E</m>, must also be equal, so <m>\phi = \chi =65\degree</m>. (Do you see why?)  The sides opposite each pair of corresponding angles are equal, so <m>AB=DE</m>, <m>BC=CD</m> and <m>AC=CE</m>.  In particular, we find that <m>z=9</m>.</p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 45%">
    <p>The two triangles at right are congruent.  Find the values of <m>\alpha</m>, <m>\beta</m>, and <m>\gamma</m>.</p>
    <image source="images/exer1-2-1.png"><description>two cong triangles</description></image></sidebyside>
</statement></exercise>

<p>Recall that the <term>altitude</term> of a triangle is the segment from one vertex of the triangle perpendicular to the opposite side.</p>

<example><statement>
    <p>Show that the altitude of an equilateral triangle divides it into two congruent right triangles.</p>
    <sidebyside width="70%"> <image source="images/exam1-2-2.png"><description>equil triangle with altitude</description></image></sidebyside>
</statement>
<solution><p> Consider for example an equilateral triangle of side 8 inches, as shown above.  The altitude is perpendicular to the base, so each half of the original triangle is a right triangle.  Because each right triangle contains a <m>60\degree</m> angle, the remaining angle in each triangle must be <m>90\degree - 60\degree = 30\degree</m>.   Both triangles have a side of length 8 between the angles of 30° and 60°, so they are congruent. (Consequently, the short sides of the congruent triangles are equal, so each is half the original base.)</p>
</solution></example>

<p> The triangles in the previous example are a special type of right triangle called <m>30\degree</m><ndash/><m>60\degree</m><ndash/><m>90\degree</m> triangles.  Notice that in these triangles, the <term>leg</term> opposite the <m>30\degree</m> angle is half the length of the <term>hypotenuse</term>.</p>

<exercise><statement>
    <sidebyside widths="50% 40%">
    <p>The diagonal of a <term>parallelogram</term> divides it into two congruent triangles, as shown at right.  List the corresponding parts of the two triangles, and explain why each pair is equal.</p>
    <image source="images/exer1-2-2.png"><description>parallelogram</description></image></sidebyside>
</statement></exercise>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Similar Triangles</title>
<p> Two triangles are <term>similar</term> if they have the same shape but not necessarily the same size.  The corresponding angles are equal, and the corresponding sides are <term>proportional</term>.  We can think of one similar triangle as an enlargement or a reduction of the other.  (See the figures below.)</p>

<sidebyside widths="35%, 20%, 35%"> <image source="images/simtri.png"><description>similar triangles</description></image>
            <image source="images/simtrieqns.png"><description>similar triangle equations</description></image>
            <image source="images/simtriproj.png"><description>similar triangles projected</description></image></sidebyside>

<p> To decide whether two triangles are similar, it turns out that we need to verify only one of the two conditions for similarity, and the other condition will be true automatically.</p>

<assemblage><title>Similar Triangles</title>
        <p>Two triangles are similar if either
            <ol label="1">
                <li> their corresponding angles are equal, or</li>
                <li> their corresponding sides are proportional.</li>
                </ol> </p>
</assemblage>

<example><statement>
    <p>Which of the pairs of triangles shown below are similar?</p>
    <p><ol label="a">
        <li><sidebyside width="35%"> <image source="images/exam1-2-3a.png"><description>sim triangles</description></image></sidebyside></li>
        <li><sidebyside width="40%"> <image source="images/exam1-2-3b.png"><description>not sim triangles</description></image></sidebyside></li>
        <li><sidebyside width="50%"> <image source="images/exam1-2-3c.png"><description>sim triangles 42 deg</description></image></sidebyside></li>
    </ol></p>
</statement>
<solution><p> 
    <ol label="a">
        <li><p>We will check whether the corresponding sides are proportional.  We compute the ratios of the corresponding sides, making sure to write each ratio in the same order, <m>\dfrac{\text{larger triangle}}{\text{smaller triangle}}</m>.  (The other order, <m>\dfrac{\text{smaller triangle}}{\text{larger triangle}}</m>,  would also work, as long as we use the same order for all the ratios.)</p>

        <sidebyside><p><m>~~~~~\text{shorter legs:}~~\dfrac{9}{6}~~~~~</m> longer legs: <m>~~\dfrac{12}{8}~~~~~</m> hypotenuses: <m>~~\dfrac{15}{10}</m></p></sidebyside> 

        <p> Because all of these ratios are equal to <m>1.5</m>, the triangles are similar.</p></li>
        <li>The ratios of corresponding sides are not equal:  the ratio of the longest sides is <m>\dfrac{6}{5}</m>, but the ratio of the smallest sides is <m>\dfrac{4}{3}</m>.  The triangles are not similar.</li>
        <li>The missing angle of the first right triangle is <m>48\degree</m>, and the missing angle in the second right triangle is <m>42\degree</m>, so three pairs of angles match.  The triangles are similar.</li></ol></p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>
    <p>Are the triangles below similar?  Explain why or why not in each case.</p>
    <p><ol label="a">
        <li><sidebyside width="45%"> <image source="images/exer1-2-3a.png"><description>sim triangles by sides</description></image></sidebyside></li>
        <li><sidebyside width="35%"> <image source="images/exer1-2-3b.png"><description>sim triangles by angles</description></image></sidebyside></li>
    </ol></p>
</statement></exercise>

<note><p>In the previous exercise, note that the third angle in each triangle must be <m>80\degree</m>, because the sum of the angles is <m>180\degree</m>.  Thus, we need only show that <em>two</em> pairs of angles are equal to show that two triangles are similar.</p></note>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Using Proportions with Similar Triangles</title>

<p> The figure in the next example shows a parallelogram <m>ABCD</m> and two triangles, <m>\triangle ABE</m> and <m>\triangle FCE</m>.  Can we find the unknown lengths <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> in the larger triangle? </p> 
 <p> First note that two pairs of corresponding angles in the triangles are equal: <m>\angle BEA</m> and <m>\angle FEC</m> are vertical angles, and <m>\angle EFC</m> and <m>\angle BAE</m> are alternate interior angles.  But if two pairs of corresponding angles are equal, then the third pair must be equal also.  This means that the two triangles are similar, and we can use the fact that their corresponding sides are proportional to find <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>.</p>

 <example><statement>
    <sidebyside widths="45% 40%"> 
        <p>Find the value of <m>x</m> in the figure at right.</p>
        <image source="images/exam1-2-4.png"><description>parallelogram triangles</description></image></sidebyside>   
</statement>
<solution><p>  We see that <m>x</m> is the length of the shortest side in <m>\triangle ABE</m>. We know the short side in <m>\triangle FCE</m> and the lengths of the medium sides in each triangle.  If we form the ratios of the short sides and the medium sides, we obtain the following proportion.</p>

<sidebyside><p><m>\dfrac{\text{larger triangle}}{\text{smaller triangle}}:~~~~~\dfrac{x}{4}~~~=~~~\dfrac{15}{6}</m></p></sidebyside>

<p>To solve the proportion, we cross-multiply to get</p>
 <p>
                \begin{align*}
                6x\amp =4(15)=60 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by }6.\\
                x\amp =\frac{60}{6} = 10  \amp \amp \\  
                \end{align*}
            </p>
</solution></example>

<warning><p>Remember that“cross-multiplying”is a short-cut technique for solving proportions.  It does not work for other operations involving fractions.</p></warning>

<exercise><statement>  
    <p>Find the value of <m>y</m> in the previous example.</p>
</statement></exercise>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Similar Right Triangles</title>

<p>If two <em>right</em> triangles have one pair of corresponding acute angles with the same measure, then the triangles are similar.  We can use this fact about right triangles to make indirect measurements.</p>

<example><statement>
     <p>Delbert would like to know the height of a certain building.  He gets Francine to hold up a 5-foot pole near the building and measures the length of its shadow.  The shadow of the pole is 3 feet long, and the shadow of the building is 12 feet long.</p>
     <p><ol label="a">  
        <li>Use similar triangles to write a proportion involving the height of the building.</li>
        <li>Solve the proportion to find the height of the building.</li></ol></p>

       <sidebyside width="60%"><image source="images/exam1-2-5.png"><description>building</description></image></sidebyside>   
</statement>
<solution>
    <p><ol label="a">  
        <li><p>In the figure above we see two right triangles:  One triangle is formed by the building and  its shadow, and the other by the pole and its shadow.  Because the light rays from the sun are parallel, the two angles at the tips of the shadows are equal.  Thus, the two right triangles are similar, and their corresponding sides are proportional.  The ratios of heights and bases in the two triangles yield the proportion</p>

<sidebyside><m>\dfrac{\text{larger triangle}}{\text{smaller triangle}}:~~~~~\dfrac{h}{5}~~~=~~~\dfrac{12}{3}</m></sidebyside></li>

        <li><p>To solve the proportion, we cross-multiply to get
            
                \begin{align*}
                3h\amp =5(12)=60 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by }3.\\
                h\amp =\frac{60}{3} = 20  \amp \amp \\  
                \end{align*}
           
            The building is 20 feet tall.</p></li></ol></p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>  
    <p>Earlier we created a 30°-60°-90° triangle in which the shorter leg was 4 inches and the hypotenuse was 8 inches.  The hypotenuse of another 30°-60°-90° triangle is 5 feet.  What is the length of the side opposite the 30° angle?</p>
</statement></exercise>

</subsection>

<subsection><title>Overlapping Triangles</title>
<p>In some applications, similar triangles may share a side or an angle.</p>

<example><statement>
       <sidebyside widths="50% 40%"><p>Identify two similar triangles in the figure at right, and write a proportion to find <m>H</m>.</p>
       <image source="images/exam1-2-6.png"><description>overlapping triangles</description></image></sidebyside>   
</statement>
<solution>
    <p> The two triangles overlap, sharing the marked angle, as shown below.  Because each triangle also has a right angle, they are similar.</p>

    <sidebyside width="75%"><image source="images/exam1-2-6soln.png"><description>separated triangles</description></image></sidebyside>

    <p>Note that the base of the larger triangle is <m>24+12=36</m>.  The ratio of the heights and the ratio of the bases must be equal, so we write the following proportion.            
                \begin{align*}
                \frac{H}{10}\amp =\frac{36}{24} \amp \amp \text{Cross-multiply.}\\
                24H\amp =360 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by }24.\\
                H\amp =\frac{360}{24} = 15  \amp \amp \\  
                \end{align*}</p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>  
    <sidebyside widths="50% 35%"><p>Heather wants to know the height of a street lamp.  She discovers that when she is 12 feet from the lamp, her shadow is 6 feet long.  Find the height of the street lamp.</p>
       <image source="images/exer1-2-6.png"><description>streetlamp</description></image></sidebyside>
</statement></exercise>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Algebra Refresher</title>

<exercises>
<exercisegroup cols="3">
        <introduction><p>Which of the following expressions and equations are proportions?</p></introduction>
    <exercise number="1"><statement>
        <p><m>\dfrac{7}{x}=\dfrac{3}{5}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="2"><statement>
         <p><m>\dfrac{x}{2}=\dfrac{8}{x+2}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="3"><statement>
        <p><m>1+\dfrac{x}{4}=\dfrac{2x}{3}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="4"><statement>
        <p><m>\dfrac{6}{x}+\dfrac{x}{5}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="5"><statement>
        <p><m>\dfrac{3}{x+1}\cdot\dfrac{2x}{5}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="6"><statement>
        <p><m>\dfrac{1}{x}+\dfrac{2}{3x}=\dfrac{x-2}{2}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>
</exercisegroup>

<exercisegroup cols="2">
        <introduction><p>Solve each equation.  Begin by writing an equivalent equation without fractions:  multiply both sides by the LCD.
</p></introduction>
    <exercise number="7"><statement>
        <p><m>\dfrac{x}{12}=\dfrac{3}{x}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>

    <exercise number="8"><statement>
        <p><m>1+\dfrac{x}{2}=\dfrac{2x}{5}</m></p></statement>
    </exercise>
</exercisegroup>
</exercises>

<subsubsection><title>Answers to 1.2 Exercises</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li> <m>\alpha = 85\degree, \beta = 75\degree, \gamma = 85\degree</m></li>
    <li><m>\angle BCA = \angle CAD</m> and <m>\angle BAC = \angle ACD</m> because they are alternate interior angles.  If two pairs of angles in a triangle are equal, so is the third pair, so <m>\angle B = \angle D</m>. <m>BC = AD</m> and <m>AB = CD</m> because they are opposite sides of a parallelogram, and <m>AC = AC</m>.</li>
    <li>a.  The triangles are similar because <m>\frac{4}{6} = \frac{6}{9} = \frac{8}{12}</m>, so the sides are proportional.
    b.  The third angle in both triangles is <m>80\degree</m>, so the triangles are similar because their corresponding angles are equal.</li>
    <li><m>y=20</m></li>
    <li>2.5 feet</li>    
    <li>15 feet</li>
</ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>Algebra Refresher Answers</title>
<p>Only 1 and 2 are proportions.</p>
<p>7.  <m>\pm 6</m></p>      
<p>8.  <m>-10</m></p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>

<subsection><title>Section 1.2 Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title> <p>Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.</p>
<p><ul cols="3">
    <li>Congruent</li>
    <li>Altitude</li>
    <li>Leg</li>
    <li>Hypotenuse</li>
    <li>Parallelogram</li>
    <li>Similar</li>
    <li>Proportional</li>
</ul></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>Concepts</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li>Two triangles are <term>congruent</term> if they have exactly the same size and shape.</li>
    <li>The <term>altitude</term> of an equilateral triangle divides it into two congruent right triangles.</li>
    <li>In a 30°-60°-90° right triangle, the <term>leg</term> opposite the 30° angle is half the length of the <term>hypotenuse</term>.</li>
    <li>Two triangles are <term>similar</term> if they have the same shape but not necessarily the same size.  The corresponding angles are equal, and the corresponding sides are <term>proportional</term>.</li>
    <li><assemblage><title>Similar Triangles</title>
        <p>Two triangles are similar if either
            <ol label="1">
                <li> their corresponding angles are equal, or</li>
                <li> their corresponding sides are proportional.</li>
                </ol> </p>
            </assemblage></li>
    <li>If two <em>right</em> triangles have <em>one</em> pair of corresponding acute angles with the same measure, then the triangles are similar.</li>
</ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>Study Questions</title>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li>What is the difference between congruent triangles and similar triangles?</li>
    <li>What is the name of the short-cut method for solving proportions?  Why does the method work?</li>
    <li>In two triangles, if two corresponding pairs of angles are equal, are the triangles similar?  How do you know?</li>
    <li><p>For the triangles shown, which of the following equations is true?  Explain why.</p>
        <sidebyside widths="35% 60%"><image source="images/1-2SQ4.png"><description>simtri</description></image>
        <p><ol label="a" cols="2">
            <li><m>\dfrac{4}{x} = \dfrac{6}{8}</m></li>
            <li><m>\dfrac{x}{4} = \dfrac{6}{8}</m></li>
            <li><m>\dfrac{x}{x+4} = \dfrac{6}{8}</m></li>
            <li><m>\dfrac{x}{x+4} = \dfrac{6}{14}</m></li>
        </ol></p>
        </sidebyside></li>
    </ol></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>Skills</title>
<p>Practice each skill in the Homework Problems listed.</p>
<p><ol label="1">
    <li>Identify congruent triangles and find unknown parts     #1-6</li>
    <li>Identify similar triangles    #7-10</li>
    <li>Find unknown parts of similar triangles    #11-20</li>
    <li>Solve problems using proportions and similar triangles    #21-26</li>
    <li>Use proportions to relate sides of similar triangles    #27-38</li>
</ol></p>
</subsubsection>




</subsection>







<xi:include href="./hmwk-1-2.xml" />
</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->