<?xml version="1.0"?>


<!-- This file was originally part of the book     -->
<!--   Modeling, Functions, and Graphs   -->
<!--           4th                                     -->
<!-- Copyright (C) Katherine Yoshiwara      -->

<exercises xml:id="section-7-5-exercises"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Homework</title>

<exercisegroup cols="4"><introduction><p>Solve each equation algebraically.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="1"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{6}{w+2}=4 </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{-1}{2} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="2"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{12}{r-7}=5 </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="3"><statement><p><m>9=\dfrac{h-5}{h-2} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{13}{8} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="4"><statement><p><m>-3=\dfrac{v+1}{v-6} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="5"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{15}{s^2}=8 </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\pm\sqrt{\dfrac{15}{8}} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="6"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{3}{m^2}=5 </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="7"><statement><p><m>4.3=\sqrt{\dfrac{18}{y}} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{1800}{1849}\approx 0.97 </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="8"><statement><p><m>6.5=\dfrac{52}{\sqrt{z}} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercise number="9"><statement><p>The total weight, <m>S</m>, that a beam can support is given in pounds by
<me>S = \frac{182.6wh^2}{l}</me>
where <m>w</m> is the width of the beam in inches, <m>h</m> is its height in inches, and <m>l</m> is the length of the beam in feet. A beam over the doorway in an interior wall of a house must support <m>1600</m> pounds. If the beam is <m>4</m> inches wide and <m>9</m> inches tall, how long can it be?</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>37</m> ft</p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="10"><statement><p>If two appliances are connected in parallel in an electrical circuit, the total resistance, <m>R</m>, in the circuit is given by
<me>R = \frac{ab}{a+b}</me>
where <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are the resistances of the two appliances. If one appliance has a resistance of <m>18</m> ohms, and the total resistance in the circuit is measured at <m>12</m> ohms, what is the resistance of the second appliance?</p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="11"><statement><p>A flock of eider ducks is making a <m>150</m>-mile flight at an average airspeed of <m>50</m> miles per hour against a moderate
headwind.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the ducks' travel time, <m>t</m>, as a function of the windspeed, <m>v</m>, and graph the function in the window
    <md>
        <mrow>
            \small{\text{Xmin}} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \small{\text{Xmax}} = 50
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            \small{\text{Ymin}} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \small{\text{Ymax}} =20
        </mrow>
    </md> (See Problem <xref ref="problem-7-4-1" text="global"/> of <xref ref="section-7-4-exercises" text="type-hybrid">Homework Section 7.4</xref>.)</p></li>
    <li><p>Write and solve an equation to find the windspeed if the flock makes its trip in <m>4</m> hours. Label the corresponding point on your graph.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>t=\dfrac{150}{50-v} </m> <image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-11.jpg"  width="60%"><description>rational function</description></image> </p></li>
    <li><p><m>4=\dfrac{150}{50-v} </m>; <m>v=12.5</m> mph</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="12"><statement><p>Bluefin tuna swim at average speed of <m>36 </m> miles per hour in still water. A school of tuna is making a <m>200</m>-mile trip against a current.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the tuna's travel time, <m>t</m>, as a function of the current speed, <m>v</m>, and graph the function in the window
    <md>
        <mrow>
            \small{\text{Xmin}} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \small{\text{Xmax}} = 36
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
            \small{\text{Ymin}} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \small{\text{Ymax}} =50
        </mrow>
    </md> (See Problem <xref ref="problem-7-4-2" text="global"/> of <xref ref="section-7-4-exercises" text="type-hybrid">Homework Section 7.4</xref>.)</p></li>
    <li><p>Write and solve an equation to find the current speed if the school makes its trip in <m>8</m> hours. Label the corresponding point on your graph.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="13"><statement><p>The cost, in thousands of dollars, for immunizing <m>p</m> percent of the residents of Emporia against a dangerous new disease is given by the function
<me>C(p) = \frac{72p}{100-p}</me>
Write and solve an equation to determine what percent
of the population can be immunized for <m>\$168,000</m>.</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>168=\dfrac{72p}{100-p}</m>; <m>p=70\%</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="14"><statement><p>The cost, in thousands of dollars, for extracting <m>p</m> percent of a precious ore from a mine is given by the function
<me>C(p) = \frac{360p}{100-p}</me>
Write and solve an equation to determine what percentage of the ore can be extracted for <m>\$390,000</m>.</p></statement>
</exercise>


<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>For Problems 15<ndash/>18,
<ol label="a">
    <li><p>Solve the equation graphically by graphing two functions, one for each side of the equation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve the equation algebraically.</p></li>
</ol></p></introduction>

<exercise number="15"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{2x}{x+1}=\dfrac{x+1}{2} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-15.jpg"  width="95%"><description>rational function and line</description></image> </p></li>
    <li><p><m>x=1</m></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="16"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{3}{2x+1}=\dfrac{2x-3}{x} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="17"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{2}{x+1}=\dfrac{x}{x+1}+1 </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-17.jpg"  width="95%"><description>two rational functions</description></image> </p></li>
    <li><p><m>x=\dfrac{1}{2} </m></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="18"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{5}{x-3}=\dfrac{x+2}{x-3}+3 </m></p></statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercise number="19"><statement><p>The manager of Joe's Burgers discovers that he will sell <m>\dfrac{160}{x} </m> burgers per day if the price of a burger is <m>x</m> dollars. On the other hand, he can afford to make <m>6x + 49</m> burgers if he charges <m>x</m> dollars apiece for them.
<ol>
    <li><p>Graph the <term>demand function</term>, <m>D(x)= \dfrac{160}{x} </m>, and the <term>supply function</term>, <m>S(x) = 6x + 49</m>, in the same window. At what price <m>x</m> does the demand for burgers equal the number that Joe can afford to supply? This value for <m>x</m> is called the <term>equilibrium price</term><idx>equilibrium price</idx>.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write and solve an equation to verify your equilibrium price.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-19.jpg"  width="95%"><description>supply and demand curves</description></image><m>~\$2.50</m> </p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{160}{x}=6x+49 </m>; <m>x=2.50</m></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>


<exercise number="20"><statement><p>A florist finds that she will sell <m>\dfrac{300}{x} </m> dozen roses per week
if she charges <m>x</m> dollars for a dozen. Her suppliers will sell her <m>5x - 55</m> dozen roses if she sells them at <m>x</m> dollars per dozen.
<ol>
    <li><p>Graph the demand function, <m>D(x)= \dfrac{300}{x} </m>, and the supply function, <m>S(x) = 5x -55</m>, in the same window. At what equilibrium price <m>x</m> will the florist sell all the roses she purchases?.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write and solve an equation to verify your equilibrium price.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="21"><statement><p>Francine wants to fence a rectangular area of <m>3200</m> square feet to grow vegetables for her family of three.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the length of the garden as a function of its width.</p></li>
    <li><p>Express the perimeter, <m>P</m>, of the garden as a function of its width.</p></li>
    <li><p>Graph your function for perimeter and find the coordinates of the lowest point on the graph. Interpret those coordinates in the context of the problem.</p></li>
    <li><p>Francine has <m>240</m> feet of chain link to make a fence for the garden, and she would like to know what the width of the garden should be. Write an equation that describes this situation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve your equation and find the dimensions of the garden.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>L=\dfrac{3200}{w} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>P=\dfrac{6400}{w}+2w </m></p></li>
    <li><p><image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-21.jpg"  width="80%"><description>rational function</description></image> Lowest point: <m>(56.6, 226)</m>; The minimum perimeter is <m>226</m> ft for a width of <m>56.6</m> ft.</p></li>
    <li><p><m>240=\dfrac{6400}{w}+2w</m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>40</m> ft by <m>80</m> ft</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="22"><statement><p>The cost of wire fencing is <m>\$7.50</m> per foot. A rancher wants to enclose a rectangular pasture of <m>1000</m> square
feet with this fencing.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the length of the pasture as a function of its width.</p></li>
    <li><p>Express the cost of the fence as a function of its width.</p></li>
    <li><p>Graph your function for the cost and find the coordinates of the lowest point on the graph. Interpret those coordinates in the context of the problem.</p></li>
    <li><p>The rancher has <m>\$1050</m> to spend on the fence, and she would like to know what the width of the pasture should be. Write an equation to describe this situation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve your equation and find the dimensions of the pasture.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="23"><statement><p>A proportion is an equation in which each side is a ratio: <m>\dfrac{a}{b} = \dfrac{c}{d} </m>. Show that this equation may be rewritten as <m>ad = bc</m>.</p></statement>
<answer><p>Multiply both sides of the equation by <m>bd</m> and simplify.
<me>\frac{a}{b}\cdot \frac{bc}{1} = \frac{c}{d} \cdot \frac{bc}{1}, \text{ so } ac=bd</me>
</p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise  number="24"><statement><p>Suppose that <m>y</m> varies directly with <m>x</m>, and <m>(a, b)</m> and
<m>(c, d)</m> are two points on the graph of <m>y</m> in terms of <m>x</m>. Show that <m>\dfrac{b}{a}=\dfrac{d}{c}</m>.</p></statement></exercise>


<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>Solve each proportion using your result from Problem 23.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="25"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{3}{4}=\dfrac{y+2}{12-y} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>4</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="26"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{-3}{4}=\dfrac{y-7}{y+14} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="27"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{50}{r}=\dfrac{75}{r+20} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>40</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="28"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{30}{r}=\dfrac{20}{r-10} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercisegroup><introduction><p>Use your result from Problem 24 to write and solve a proportion for the problem.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="29"><statement><p>Property taxes on a house vary directly with the value of the house. If the taxes on a house worth <m>\$120,000</m> are <m>\$2700</m>, what would the taxes be on a house assessed at <m>\$275,000</m>?</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\$6187.50</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="30"><statement><p>The cost of electricity varies directly with the number of units (BTUs) consumed. If a typical household in the Midwest uses <m>83</m> million BTUs of electricity annually and pays <m>\$1236</m>, how much will a household that uses <m>70</m> million BTUs annually spend for energy?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="31"><statement><p>Distances on a map vary directly with actual distances. The scale on a map of Michigan uses <m>\frac{3}{8} </m> inch to represent
<m>10</m> miles. If Isle Royale is <m>1\frac{11}{16} </m>
16 inches long on the map, what is the actual length of the island?</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>45</m> mi</p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="32"><statement><p>The dimensions of an enlargement vary directly with the dimensions of the original. A photographer plans to enlarge a photograph that measures <m>8.3</m> centimeters by <m>11.2</m> centimeters to produce a poster that is <m>36</m> centimeters wide. How long will the poster be?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="33"><statement><p>The Forest Service tags <m>200</m> perch and releases them into Spirit Lake. One month later, it captures <m>80</m> perch and finds that <m>18</m> of them are tagged. What is the Forest
Service's estimate of the original perch population of the
lake?</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>689</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="34"><statement><p>The Wildlife Commission tags <m>30</m> Canada geese at one of its migratory feeding grounds. When the geese return, the commission captures <m>45</m> geese, of which <m>4</m> are tagged. What is the commission's estimate of the
number of geese that use the feeding ground?</p></statement></exercise>

<exercise number="35"><statement><p>The highest point on Earth is Mount Everest in Tibet, with an elevation of <m>8848</m> meters. The deepest part of the ocean is the Challenger Deep in the Mariana Trench, near Indonesia, <m>11,034</m> meters below sea level.
<ol>
    <li><p>What is the total height variation in the surface of the Earth?</p></li>
    <li><p>What percentage of the Earth's radius, <m>6400</m> kilometers, is this variation?</p></li>
    <li><p>If the Earth were shrunk to the size of a basketball, with a radius of <m>4.75</m> inches, what would be the corresponding height of Mount Everest?</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="3">
    <li><p><m>19,882</m> m</p></li>
    <li><p><m>0.3\%</m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>0.00657</m> in</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="36"><statement><p>Shortly after the arrival of human beings at the Hawaiian islands around 400 A.D., many species of birds became extinct. Fossils of <m>29</m> different species have been found, but some species may have left no fossils for us to find. We can estimate the total number of extinct species using a proportion. Of <m>9</m> species that are still alive, biologists have found fossil evidence of <m>7</m>. (Source: Burton, 1998)
<ol>
    <li><p>Assuming that the same fraction of extinct species have left fossil records, calculate the total number of extinct species</p></li>
    <li><p>Give two reasons why this estimate may not be completely accurate.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercise number="37"><statement><p>In the figure, the rectangle <m>ABCD</m> is divided into a square and a smaller rectangle, <m>CDEF</m>. The two rectangles <m>ABCD</m> and <m>CDEF</m> are similar (their corresponding sides are proportional.) A rectangle <m>ABCD</m> with this property is called a <term>golden rectangle</term><idx>golden rectangle</idx>, and the ratio of its length to its width is called the golden ratio.
<sidebyside widths="65% 25%" valigns="middle middle"><p>The golden ratio appears
frequently in art and nature, and it is considered to give the most pleasing proportions to many figures. We will compute the golden ratio as follows.</p>
<image source="images/fig-7-5-37">
  <description>
    golden rectangle
  </description>
</image>
</sidebyside>
<ol>
    <li><p>Let <m>AB = 1</m> and <m>AD = x</m>. What are the lengths of <m>AE</m>, <m>DE</m>, and <m>CD</m>?</p></li>
    <li><p>Write a proportion in terms of <m>x</m> for the similarity of rectangles <m>ABCD</m> and <m>CDEF</m>. Be careful to match up the corresponding sides.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve your proportion for <m>x</m>. Find the golden ratio, <m>\dfrac{AD}{AB}=\dfrac{x}{1} </m>.</p></li>
</ol>
</p></statement>
<answer><p><ol >
    <li><p><m>AE = 1,~ DE = x - 1,~ CD = 1</m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{1}{x}=\dfrac{x-1}{x} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{1+\sqrt{5}}{2} </m></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="38"><statement><p><sidebyside widths="65% 25%" valigns="middle middle"><p>The figure shows the graphs of two equations, <m>y = x</m> and <m>y=\dfrac{1}{x}+1 </m>.</p><image source="images/fig-7-5-38"><description>line and translated reciprocal</description></image></sidebyside> 
<ol>
    <li><p>Find the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the intersection point of the two graphs.</p></li>
    <li><p>Compare your answer to the golden ratio you computed in Problem 37.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>


<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>Solve each formula for the specified variable.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="39"><statement><p><m>S=\dfrac{a}{1-r} </m>, for <m>r</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>r=\dfrac{S-a}{S} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="40"><statement><p><m>I=\dfrac{E}{r+R} </m>, for <m>R</m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="41"><statement><p><m>H=\dfrac{2xy}{x+y} </m>, for <m>x</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>x=\dfrac{Hy}{2y-H} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="42"><statement><p><m>M=\dfrac{ab}{a+b} </m>, for <m>b</m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="43"><statement><p><m>F=\dfrac{Gm_1 m_2}{d^2} </m>, for <m>d</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>d=\pm \sqrt{\dfrac{Gm_1 m_2}{F}} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="44"><statement><p><m>F=\dfrac{kq_1 q_2}{r^2} </m>, for <m>r</m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="45"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{1}{Q} + \dfrac{1}{I} = \dfrac{2}{r} </m>, for <m>r</m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>r=\dfrac{2QI}{I+Q} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="46"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{1}{R} =\dfrac{1}{A}+\dfrac{1}{B} </m>, for <m>B</m></p></statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercise number="47"><statement><p>The sidereal period of a planet is the time for the planet to make one trip around the Sun (as seen from the Sun itself). The synodic period is the time between two successive conjunctions of the planet and the Sun, as seen from Earth. The relationship among the sidereal period, <m>P</m>, of a planet, the synodic period, <m>S</m>, of the
planet, and the sidereal period of Earth, <m>E</m>, is given by
<me>\frac{1}{P}=\frac{1}{S}+\frac{1}{E} </me> when the planet is closer to the Sun than the Earth is. Solve for <m>P</m> in terms of <m>S</m> and <m>E</m>.</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>P=\dfrac{ES}{E+S} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="48"><statement><p>When a planet is farther from the Sun than Earth is,
<me>\frac{1}{P}=\frac{1}{E}-\frac{1}{S} </me>  where <m>P</m>, <m>E</m>, and <m>S</m> are as defined in Problem 47. Solve for <m>P</m> in terms of <m>S</m> and <m>E</m>.</p></statement></exercise>


<exercisegroup cols="2"><introduction><p>Solve the equation algebraically.</p></introduction>

<exercise number="49"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{3}{x-2}=\dfrac{1}{2}+\dfrac{2x-7}{2x-4} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>5</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="50"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{2}{x+1}+\dfrac{1}{3x+3}=\dfrac{1}{6} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="51"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{4}{x+2}-\dfrac{1}{x}=\dfrac{2x-1}{x^2+2x} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>1</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="52"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{1}{x-1} +\dfrac{2}{x+1}=\dfrac{x-2}{x^2-1} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="53"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{x}{x+2} -\dfrac{3}{x-2}=\dfrac{x^2+8}{x^2-4} </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{-14}{5} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="54"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{4}{2x-3} +\dfrac{4x}{4x^2-9} = \dfrac{1}{2x+3} </m></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="55"><statement><p><m>\dfrac{4}{3x} + \dfrac{3}{3x+1}+2=0 </m></p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{-1}{6}, \dfrac{-4}{3} </m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="56"><statement><p><m>-3= \dfrac{-10}{x+2} +\dfrac{10}{x+5}  </m></p></statement>
</exercise>
</exercisegroup>


<exercise number="57"><statement><p>A chartered sightseeing flight over the Grand Canyon is scheduled to return to its departure point in <m>3</m> hours. The pilot would like to cover a distance of <m>144</m> miles before turning around, and he hears on the Weather Service that there will be a headwind of <m>20</m> miles per hour on the outward journey.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the time it takes for the outward journey as a function of the airspeed of the plane.</p></li>
    <li><p>Express the time it takes for the return journey as a function of the speed of the plane.</p></li>
    <li><p>Graph the sum of the two functions and find the point on the graph with <m>y</m>-coordinate <m>3</m>. Interpret the coordinates of the point in the context of the problem.</p></li>
    <li><p>The pilot would like to know what airspeed to maintain in order to complete the tour in <m>3</m> hours. Write an equation to describe this situation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve your equation to find the appropriate airspeed.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>t_1=\dfrac{144}{s-20} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>t_2=\dfrac{144}{s+20} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><image source="images/fig-ans-7-5-57.jpg"  width="80%"><description>rational function</description></image> </p><p>If the airspeed is <m>100</m> mph, then the airplane will complete the round trip in <m>3</m> hours.</p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{144}{s-20}+\dfrac{144}{s+20}=3 </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>100</m> mph</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="58"><statement><p>Two student pilots leave the airport at the same time. They both fly at an airspeed of <m>180</m> miles per hour, but one flies with the wind and the other flies against the
wind.
<ol>
    <li><p>Express the time it takes the first pilot to travel <m>500</m> miles as a function of the windspeed.</p></li>
    <li><p>Express the time it takes the second pilot to travel <m>400</m> miles as a function of the windspeed.</p></li>
    <li><p>Graph the two functions in the same window, and find the coordinates of the intersection point. Interpret those coordinates in the context of the problem.</p></li>
    <li><p>Both pilots check in with their instructors at the same time, and the first pilot has traveled <m>500</m> miles while the second pilot has gone <m>400</m> miles. Write an equation to describe this situation.</p></li>
    <li><p>Solve your equation to find the speed of the wind.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
</exercise>

<exercise number="59"><statement><p>Andy drives <m>300</m> miles to Lake Tahoe at <m>70</m> miles per hour and returns home at <m>50</m> miles per hour. What is his average speed for the round trip? (It is not <m>60</m> miles per hour!)
<ol>
    <li><p>Write expressions for the time it takes for each leg of the trip if Andy drives a distance, <m>d</m>, at speed <m>r_1</m> and returns at speed <m>r_2</m>.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write expressions for the total distance and total time for the trip.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write an expression for the average speed for the entire trip.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write your answer to part (c) as a simple fraction.</p></li>
    <li><p>Use your formula to answer the question stated in the problem.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement>
<answer><p><ol cols="2">
    <li><p><m>t_1=\dfrac{d}{r_1}, ~t_2=\dfrac{d}{r_2} </m></p></li>
    <li><p>Total distance is <m>2d</m>; total time <m>\dfrac{d}{r_1}+ \dfrac{d}{r_2} </m>.</p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{2d}{\dfrac{d}{r_1}+\dfrac{d}{r_2}} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>\dfrac{2r_1 r_2}{r_1+r_2} </m></p></li>
    <li><p><m>58\frac{1}{3}</m> mph</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<exercise number="60"><statement><p>The owner of a print shop volunteers to produce flyers for his candidate's campaign. His large printing press can complete the job in <m>4</m> hours, and the smaller model can finish the flyers in <m>6</m> hours. How long will it take to
print the flyers if he runs both presses simultaneously?
<ol>
    <li><p>Suppose that the large press can complete a job in <m>t_1</m> hours and the smaller press takes <m>t_2</m> hours. Write expressions for the fraction of a job that each press can complete in <m>1</m> hour.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write an expression for the fraction of a job that can be completed in <m>1</m> hour with both presses running simultaneously.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write an expression for the amount of time needed to complete the job with both presses running.</p></li>
    <li><p>Write your answer to part (c) as a simple fraction.</p></li>
    <li><p>Use your formula to answer the question stated in the problem.</p></li>
</ol></p></statement></exercise>

</exercises> 