<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="appendix-Facts-from-Geometry"><title>Facts from Geometry</title><introduction>
<p>
    In this section, we review some information you will need from geometry. You are already familiar with the formulas for the area and perimeter of common geometric figures; you can find these formulas in the reference section <xref ref="geometry" text="title"/>.
</p></introduction>
<subsection><title>Right Triangles and the Pythagorean Theorem</title>
<p>
    A <term>right triangle</term><idx>right triangle</idx> is a triangle in which one of the angles is a right angle, or <m>90\degree</m>. Because the sum of the three angles in any triangle is <m>180\degree</m>, this means that the other two angles in a right triangle must have a sum of <m>180\degree-90\degree</m>, or <m>90\degree</m>.</p>
    <p> For instance, if we know that one of the angles in a right triangle is <m>37\degree</m>, then the remaining angle must be <m>90\degree-37\degree</m>, or <m>53\degree</m>, as shown in <xref ref="fig-right-triangle"/>.
    <figure xml:id="fig-right-triangle"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-right-triangle"  width="30%"><description>right triangle with a 37 deg and a 53 deg angle</description></image> </figure>
</p>
<example>
	<p>
		In a right triangle, the medium-sized angle is <m>15\degree</m> less than twice the smallest angle. Find the sizes of the three angles in <xref ref="fig-right-triangle2"/>.
	    <figure xml:id="fig-right-triangle2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-right-triangle2"  width="25%"><description>right triangle</description></image> </figure>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol>
			<li><title>Step 1</title><p>
				Let <m>x</m> stand for the size of the smallest angle. Then the medium-sized angle must be <m>2x-15</m>.
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 2</title><p>
				Because the right angle is the largest angle, the sum of the smallest and medium-sized angles must be the remaining <m>90\degree</m>. Thus,
				<me>x + (2x - 15) = 90</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 3</title><p>
				Solve the equation. Begin by simplifying the left side.
				<md>
					<mrow>3x - 15 \amp = 90\amp\amp\text{Add 15 to both sides.} </mrow>
					<mrow>3x \amp = 105\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 3.}</mrow>
					<mrow>x \amp = 35</mrow>
				</md>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 4</title><p>
				The smallest angle is <m>35\degree</m>, and the medium-sized angle is <m>2(35\degree) -15\degree</m>, or <m>55\degree</m>.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>
<p>
	In a right triangle (see <xref ref="fig-right-triangle3" text="type-global"/>), the longest side is opposite the right angle and is called the <term>hypotenuse</term><idx>hypotenuse</idx>. Ordinarily, even if we know the lengths of two sides of a triangle, it is not easy to find the length of the third side (to solve this problem we need trigonometry), but for the special case of a right triangle, there is an equation that relates the lengths of the three sides. This property of right triangles was known to many ancient cultures, and we know it today by the name of a Greek mathematician, Pythagoras, who provided a proof of the result.
    <figure xml:id="fig-right-triangle3"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-right-triangle3"  width="40%"><description>right triangle</description></image> </figure>
</p>

<assemblage><title>Pythagorean Theorem</title>
<p>
	In a right triangle, if <m>c</m> stands for the length of the hypotenuse and <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> stand for the lengths of the two sides, then
	<me>a^2 + b^2 = c^2</me>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
	<p>
		The hypotenuse of a right triangle is <m>15</m> feet long. The third side is twice the length of the shortest side. Find the lengths of the other 2 sides.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol>
			<li><title>Step 1</title><p>
				Let <m>x</m> represent the length of the shortest side, so that the third side has length <m>2x</m>. (See <xref ref="fig-right-triangle4" text="type-global"/>.)
			    <figure xml:id="fig-right-triangle4"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-right-triangle4"  width="50%"><description>right triangle</description></image> </figure>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 2</title><p>
				Substituting these expressions into the Pythagorean theorem, we find
				<me>x^2+(2x)^2=15^2</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 3</title><p>
				This is a quadratic equation with no linear term, so we simplify and then isolate <m>x^2</m>.
				<md>
					<mrow>x^2+4x^2\amp =225\amp\amp\text{Combine like terms.} </mrow>
					<mrow>5x^2\amp = 225\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by 5.} </mrow>
					<mrow>x^2\amp = 45</mrow>
				</md>
				Taking square roots of both sides yields
				<me>x=\pm\sqrt{45}\approx\pm 6.708203932 </me>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 4</title><p>
				Because a length must be a positive number, the shortest side has length approximately <m>6.71</m> feet, and the third side has length <m>2 (6.71)</m>, or approximately <m>13.42</m> feet.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Isosceles and Equilateral Triangles</title>
<p>
	Recall also that an <term>isosceles</term><idx>isosceles</idx> triangle is one that has at least two sides of equal length. In an isosceles triangle, the angles opposite the equal sides, called the <term>base</term><idx>base</idx> angles, are equal in measure, as shown in <xref ref="fig-isosceles-and-equilateral" text="type-global"/>a. In an equilateral triangle (<xref ref="fig-isosceles-and-equilateral" text="type-global"/>b), all three sides have equal length, and all three angles have equal measure.
<figure xml:id="fig-isosceles-and-equilateral"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-isosceles-and-equilateral"  width="50%"><description>isoscles and equilateral triangles</description></image> </figure>
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>The Triangle Inequality</title>
<p>
	The longest side in a triangle is always opposite the largest angle, and the shortest side is opposite the smallest angle.</p>
	<p> It is also true that the sum of the lengths of any two sides of a triangle must be greater than the third side, or else the two sides will not meet to form a triangle! This fact is called the <term>triangle inequality</term><idx>triangle inequality</idx>.
</p>
<p>
	In <xref ref="fig-oblique-triangle" text="type-global"/>, we must have that
	<me>p + q \gt r</me>
	where <m>p</m>, <m>q</m>, and <m>r</m> are the lengths of the sides of the triangle.
<figure xml:id="fig-oblique-triangle"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-oblique-triangle"  width="30%"><description>triangle of sides p, q, and r</description></image> </figure>
</p>
<p>
	Now we can use the triangle inequality to discover information about the sides of a triangle.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Two sides of a triangle have lengths <m>7</m> inches and <m>10</m> inches. What can you say about the length of the third side (see <xref ref="fig-oblique-triangle2" text="type-global"/>)?
		<figure xml:id="fig-oblique-triangle2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-oblique-triangle2"  width="40%"><description>triangle with two sides of length 7 and 10 inches</description></image> </figure>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		Let <m>x</m> represent the length of the third side of the triangle. By the triangle inequality, we must have that
		<me>x \lt 7 + 10, ~~~\text{ or }~~~ x \ly 17</me>
		Looking at another pair of sides, we must also have that
		<me>10 \lt x + 7, ~~~\text{ or }~~~  x \gt 3</me>
		Thus the third side must be greater than <m>3</m> inches but less than <m>17</m> inches long.
	</p>
</solution></example>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Similar Triangles</title>
<p>
	Two triangles are said to be <term>similar</term><idx>similar</idx> if their corresponding angles are equal. This means that the two triangles will have the same shape but not necessarily the same size. One of the triangles will be an enlargement or a reduction of the other; so their corresponding sides are proportional.</p>
	<p> In other words, <em>for similar triangles, the ratios of the corresponding sides are equal</em> (see <xref ref="fig-similar-triangles" text="type-global"/>).
	<figure xml:id="fig-similar-triangles"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-similar-triangles"  width="70%"><description>similar triangle</description></image> </figure>
</p>
<p>
	If any two pairs of corresponding angles of two triangles are equal, then the third pair must also be equal, because in both triangles the sum of the angles is <m>180\degree</m>. Thus, to show that two triangles are similar, we need only show that two pairs of angles are equal.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		The roof of an A-frame ski chalet forms an isosceles triangle with the floor as the base (see <xref ref="fig-A-frame-roof" text="type-global"/>). The floor of the chalet is <m>24</m> feet wide, and the ceiling is <m>20</m> feet tall at the center. If a loft is built at a height of <m>8</m> feet from the floor, how wide will the loft be?
	</p>
<sidebyside widths="35% 30%" margins="auto">
	<figure xml:id="fig-A-frame-roof"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-A-frame-roof"><description>dimensions of A-frame roof</description></image> </figure>
	<figure xml:id="fig-A-frame-roof2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-A-frame-roof2"><description>dimensions of A-frame roof</description></image> </figure>

</sidebyside>
<solution>
	<p>
		From <xref ref="fig-A-frame-roof2" text="type-global"/>, we can show that <m>\Delta ABC</m> is similar to <m>\Delta ADE</m>. Both triangles include <m>\angle A</m>, and because <m>\overline{DE}</m> is parallel to <m>\overline{BC} </m>, <m>\angle ADE</m> is equal to <m>\angle ABC</m>. Thus, the triangles have two pairs of equal angles and are therefore similar triangles.
		<ol>
			<li><title>Step 1</title><p>
				Let <m>w</m> stand for the width of the loft.
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 2</title><p>
				First note that if <m>FG = 8</m>, then <m>AF = 12</m>. Because <m>\Delta ABC</m> is similar to <m>\Delta ADE</m>, the ratios of their corresponding sides (or corresponding altitudes) are equal. In particular,
				<me>\frac{w}{24}=\frac{12}{20}  </me>				
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 3</title><p>
				Solve the proportion for <m>w</m>. Begin by cross-multiplying.
				<md>
					<mrow>
						20w \amp = (12)(24)\amp\amp\text{Apply the fundamental principle.}
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						w \amp = \frac{288}{20}= 14.4\amp\amp\text{Divide by 20.}
					</mrow>
				</md>
			</p></li>
			<li><title>Step 4</title><p>
				The floor of the loft will be <m>14.4</m> feet wide.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Volume and Surface Area</title>
<p>The <term>volume</term><idx>volume</idx> of a three-dimensional object measures its capacity, or how much space it encloses. Volume is measured in cubic units, such as cubic inches or cubic meters.</p>

	<figure xml:id="fig-box2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-box2"  width="30%"><description>box</description></image> </figure>
	
	<p> The volume of a rectangular prism, or box, is given by the product of its length, width, and height. For example, the volume of the box of length <m>4</m> inches, width <m>3</m> inches, and height <m>2</m> inches shown in <xref ref="fig-box2" text="type-global"/> is
	<me>V = lwh = 4(3)(2) = 24 \text{ cubic inches}</me>
</p>
<p>
	Formulas for the volumes of other common objects can be found inside the front cover of the book.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		A cylindrical can must have a height of <m>6</m> inches, but it can have any reasonable radius.
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				Write an algebraic expression for the volume of the can in terms of its radius.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				If the volume of the can should be approximately <m>170</m> cubic inches, what should its radius be?
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				The formula for the volume of a right circular cylinder is <m>V = \pi r^2h</m>. If the height of the cylinder is <m>6</m> inches, then <m>V = \pi r^2 (6)</m>, or <m>V = 6\pi r^2</m>. (See <xref ref="fig-cylinder" text="type-global"/>.)
				<figure xml:id="fig-cylinder"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-cylinder"  width="25%"><description>cylinder</description></image> </figure>	
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Substitute <m>170</m> for <m>V</m> and solve for <m>r</m>.
				<md>
					<mrow>
						170 \amp = 6\pi r^2\amp\amp\text{Divide both sides by }6\pi.
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						r^2 \amp = \frac{170}{6\pi} \amp\amp\text{Take square roots.}
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						r \amp = \sqrt{\frac{170}{6\pi}}\approx 3.00312
					</mrow>
				</md>
				Thus, the radius of the can should be approximately <m>3</m> inches. A calculator keying sequence for the expression above is
				<me>\boxed{\sqrt{~}} \,\boxed{(} \, 170 \, \boxed{\div} \, \boxed{(} \, 6 \, \boxed{\pi} \, \boxed{)}  \, \boxed{)} \, \boxed{\text{ENTER}} </me>
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>

<p>
	The <term>surface area</term><idx>surface area</idx> of a solid object is the sum of the areas of all the exterior faces of the object. It measures the amount of paper that would be needed to cover the object entirely. Since it is an area, it is measured in square units.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Write a formula for the surface area of a closed box in terms of its length, width, and height. (See <xref ref="fig-box2a" text="type-global"/>.)
		<figure xml:id="fig-box2a"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-box2"  width="30%"><description>box</description></image> </figure>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		The box has six sides; we must find the area of each side and add them.
		<ul>
		<li> The top and bottom of the box each have area <m>lw</m>, so together they contribute <m>2lw</m> to the surface area.</li>
		<li> The back and front of the box each have area <m>lh</m>, so they contribute <m>2lh</m> to the surface area.</li>
		<li> Finally, the left and right sides of the box each have area <m>wh</m>, so they add <m>2wh</m> to the surface area.</li>
		</ul>
		 Thus, the total surface area is
		<me>S = 2lw + 2lh + 2wh</me>
	</p>
</solution></example>

<p>
	Formulas for the surface areas of other common solids can be found on the insert in the front of the book.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>The Distance Formula</title>
<p>
	By using the Pythagorean theorem, we can derive a formula for the distance between two points, <m>P_1</m> and <m>P_2</m>, in terms of their coordinates.</p>
	<p> We first draw and label a right triangle as follows.</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li> Draw a horizontal line through <m>P_1</m> and a vertical line through <m>P_2</m>.</li>
	<li> These lines meet at a point <m>P_3</m>, as shown in <xref ref="fig-distance-formula" text="type-global"/>.</li>
	<li> The <m>x</m>-coordinate of <m>P_3</m> is the same as the <m>x</m>-coordinate of <m>P_2</m>, and the <m>y</m>-coordinate of <m>P_3</m> is the same as the <m>y</m>-coordinate of <m>P_1</m>. Thus, the coordinates of <m>P_3</m> are <m>(x_2, y_1)</m>.</li>
</ul></p>
	<figure xml:id="fig-distance-formula"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-distance-formula"  width="70%"><description>box</description></image> </figure>

<p>
	The distance between <m>P_1</m> and <m>P_3</m> is <m>\abs{x_2-x_1}</m> , and the distance between <m>P_2</m> and <m>P_3</m> is <m>\abs{y_2-y_1} </m>. (See <xref ref="AbsoluteValue" text="type-global"/> to review distance and absolute value.)</p>
	<p> These two numbers are the lengths of the legs of the right triangle. The length of the hypotenuse is the distance between <m>P_1</m> and <m>P_2</m>, which we will call <m>d</m>. By the Pythagorean theorem,
	<me>d^2 = (x_2 - x_1)^2 + (y_2 - y_1)^2</me>
	Taking the (positive) square root of each side of this equation gives us the <term>distance formula</term><idx>distance formula</idx>.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Distance Formula</title><idx>distance formula</idx>
<p>
	The <term>distance</term> <m>d</m> between points <m>P_1(x_1, y_1)</m> and <m>P_2(x_2, y_2)</m> is
	<me>d=\sqrt{(x_2 - x_1)^2 + (y_2 - y_1)^2} </me>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example xml:id="example-distance-formula">
	<p>
		Find the distance between <m>(2, -1)</m> and <m>(4, 3)</m>.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		Substitute <m>(2, -1)</m> for <m>(x_1, y_1)</m> and substitute <m>(4, 3)</m> for <m>(x_2, y_2)</m> in the distance formula to obtain
		<md>
			<mrow>
				d\amp =\sqrt{(x_2 - x_1)^2 + (y_2 - y_1)^2}
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				\amp =\sqrt{(4 - 2)^2 + \left[3 - (-1)\right]^2} 
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				\amp = \sqrt{4+16}=\sqrt{20}\approx 4.47
			</mrow>
		</md>		
	</p>
</solution></example>

<note><p>
	In <xref ref="example-distance-formula" text="type-global"/>, we obtain the same answer if we use <m>(4, 3)</m> for <m>P_1</m> and use <m>(2,-1)</m> for <m>P_2</m>:
		<md>
			<mrow>
				d\amp =\sqrt{(2-4)^2 + \left[(-1)-3\right]^2} 
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				\amp = \sqrt{4+16}=\sqrt{20}
			</mrow>
		</md>
</p></note>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>The Midpoint Formula</title>
<p>
	If we know the coordinates of two points, we can calculate the coordinates of the point halfway between them using the <term>midpoint</term><idx>midpoint</idx> formula. Each coordinate of the midpoint is the average of the corresponding coordinates of the two points.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Midpoint Formula</title><idx>midpoint formula</idx>
<p>
	The <term>midpoint</term><idx>midpoint</idx> of the line segment joining the points <m>P_1(x_1, y_1)</m> and <m>P_2(x_2, y_2)</m> is the point <m>M(\overline{x}, \overline{y})</m>, where
	<me>
		\overline{x} = \frac{x_1 + x_2}{2} ~~~\text{ and }~~~
		\overline{y} = \frac{y_1 + y_2}{2}
	</me>
</p>
</assemblage>

<example>
	<p>
		Find the midpoint of the line segment joining the points <m>(-2, 1)</m> and <m>(4, 3)</m>.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		Substitute <m>(-2, 1)</m> for <m>(x_1, y_1)</m> and <m>(4, 3)</m> for <m>(x_2, y_2)</m> in the midpoint formula to obtain
		<md>
			<mrow>
				\overline{x} \amp= \frac{x_1 + x_2}{2}=\frac{-2+4}{2}=1\amp\amp\text{and}
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				\overline{y} \amp= \frac{y_1 + y_2}{2}=\frac{1+3}{2}=2
			</mrow>
		</md>
		The midpoint of the segment is the point <m>(\overline{x}, \overline{y}) = (1, 2)</m>.
	</p>
</solution></example>
</subsection>


<subsection><title>Circles</title>
<p>
	A <term>circle</term><idx>circle</idx> is the set of all points in a plane that lie at a given distance, called the <term>radius</term><idx>radius</idx>, from a fixed point called the <term>center</term><idx>center</idx>.</p>
	<p> We can use the distance formula to find an equation for a circle. First consider the circle in <xref ref="fig-circles" text="type-global"/>a, whose center is the origin, <m>(0, 0)</m>.
	<figure xml:id="fig-circles"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-circles"  width="75%"><description>a circle centered at origin and a circle centered at (h,k)</description></image> </figure>
</p>
<p>
	The distance from the origin to any point <m>P(x, y)</m> on the circle is <m>r</m>. Therefore,
	<me>\sqrt{(x - 0)^2 + (y - 0)^2} = r </me>
	Or, squaring both sides,
	<me>(x - 0)^2 + (y - 0)^2 = r^2</me>
	Thus, the equation for a circle of radius <m>r</m> centered at the origin is
	<me>x^2 + y^2 = r^2</me>
</p>
<p>
	Now consider the circle in <xref ref="fig-circles" text="type-global"/>b, whose center is the point <m>(h, k)</m>. Every point <m>P(x, y)</m> on the circle lies a distance <m>r</m> from <m>(h, k)</m>, so the equation of the circle is given by the following formula.
</p>
<assemblage><title>Standard Form for a Circle</title>
<p>
	The equation for a <term>circle</term><idx>circle</idx> of <term>radius</term><idx>radius</idx> <m>r</m> centered at the point <m>(h, k)</m> is
	<me>(x - h)^2 + (y - k)^2 = r^2</me>
</p>
</assemblage>
<p>
	This equation is the <term>standard form</term><idx>standard form</idx> for a circle of radius <m>r</m> with center at <m>(h, k)</m>. It is easy to graph a circle if its equation is given in standard form.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Graph the circles.
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p><m>
				(x - 2)^2 + (y + 3)^2 = 16
			</m></p></li>
			<li><p><m>
				x^2 + (y - 4)^2 = 7
			</m></p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p><ol label="a">
		<li><p>
			The graph of <m>(x - 2)^2 + (y + 3)^2 = 16</m> is a circle with radius <m>4</m> and center at <m>(2, -3)</m>. To sketch the graph, first locate the center of the circle. (The center is not part of the graph of the circle.) From the center, move a distance of <m>4</m> units (the radius of the circle) in each of four directions: up, down, left, and right. This locates four points that lie on the circle: <m>(2, 1)</m>, <m>(2, -7)</m>, <m>(-2, -3)</m>, and <m>(6, -3)</m>. Sketch the circle through these four points. (See <xref ref="fig-circles2" text="type-global"/>a.)
			<figure xml:id="fig-circles2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-circles2"  width="80%"><description>two circles</description></image> </figure>
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			The graph of <m>x^2 + (y - 4)^2 = 7</m> is a circle with radius <m>\sqrt{7} </m> and center at <m>(0, 4)</m>. From the center, move <m>\sqrt{7} </m>, or approximately <m>2.6</m>, units in each of the four coordinate directions to obtain the points <m>(0, 6.6)</m>, <m>(0, 1.4)</m>, <m>(-2.6, 4)</m>, and <m>(2.6, 4)</m>. Sketch the circle through these four points. (See <xref ref="fig-circles2" text="type-global"/>b.)
		</p></li>
	</ol></p>
</solution></example>

<p>
	We can write an equation for any circle if we can find its center and radius.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Find an equation for the circle whose diameter has endpoints <m>(7, 5)</m> and <m>(1,-1)</m>.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		The center of the circle is the midpoint of its diameter (see <xref ref="fig-circle-irrational-radius" text="type-global"/>). Use the midpoint formula to find the center:
		<figure xml:id="fig-circle-irrational-radius"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-circle-irrational-radius"  width="30%"><description>circle with given endpoints of a diameter</description></image> </figure>
		<md>
			<mrow>
				h = \overline{x} = \frac{7 + 1}{2}= 4
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				k = \overline{y} = \frac{ 5 - 1}{2}= 2
			</mrow>
		</md>
		Thus, the center is the point <m>(h, k) = (4, 2)</m>. The radius is the distance from the center to either of the endpoints of the diameter, say the point <m>(7, 5)</m>. Use the distance formula with the points <m>(7, 5)</m> and <m>(4, 2)</m> to find the radius.
		<md>
			<mrow>
				r\amp =\sqrt{(7 - 4)^2 + (5 - 2)^2}
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				\amp = \sqrt{3^2 + 3^2}=\sqrt{18}
			</mrow>
		</md>
		Finally, substitute <m>4</m> for <m>h</m> and <m>2</m> for <m>k</m> (the coordinates of the center) and <m>\sqrt{18} </m> for <m>4</m> (the radius) into the standard form to obtain
		<md>
			<mrow>
				(x - h)^2 + (y - k)^2 \amp= r^2
			</mrow>
			<mrow>
				(x - 4)^2 + (y - 2)^2 \amp = 18
			</mrow>
		</md>
	</p>
</solution>
</example>

</subsection>

</section>

<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->