<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<section xml:id="Graphing-Rational-Functions"   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Graphing Rational Functions</title>
<introduction>
<p>
	A rational function is the quotient of two polynomials. (As with rational numbers, the word <em>rational</em> refers to a ratio.)
</p>

<xi:include href="./assemblage-rational-function.xml" />

<p>
	The graphs of rational functions can be quite different from the graphs of polynomials.
</p>

<example xml:id="example-pedal-aircraft">
	<p>
		Francine is planning a 60-mile training flight through the desert on her cycle-plane, a pedal-driven aircraft. If there is no wind, she can pedal at an average speed of 15 miles per hour, so she can complete the flight in 4 hours. 
		<ol label="a">
			<li>
				<p>If there is a headwind of <m>x</m> miles per hour, it will take Francine longer to fly 60 miles. Express the time it will take to complete the training flight as a function of <m>x</m>.</p>
			</li>
			<li><p>
				Make a table of values for the function.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Graph the function and explain what it tells you about the time Francine should allot for the flight.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				If there is a headwind of <m>x</m> miles per hour, Francine's ground speed will be <m>15 - x</m> miles per hour. Using the fact that time <m>\text{time} = \dfrac{\text{distance}}{\text{rate}}</m>, we find that the time needed for the flight will be
				<me>
					t = f (x) = \frac{60}{15 - x}
				</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				We evaluate the function for several values of <m>x</m>, as shown in the table below.</p><p>
				<sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
			        <row bottom="minor">
			            <cell><m>x</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>0</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>3</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>7</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>9</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>10</m></cell>
			        </row>
			        <row>
			            <cell><m>t</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>6</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>7.5</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>10</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>12</m></cell>
			        </row>
			    </tabular></sidebyside>
			    For example, if the headwind is <m>\alert{5}</m> miles per hour, then
			    <me>
			    	t=\frac{60}{15-\alert{5}}=\frac{60}{10}=6
			    </me>
			    Francine's effective speed is only <m>10</m> miles per hour, and it will take her <m>6</m> hours to fly the <m>60</m> miles. The table shows that as the speed of the headwind increases, the time required for the flight increases also.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				The graph of the function is shown in <xref ref="fig-graph-time-against-headwind" text="type-global"/>. You can use your calculator with the window
				<md>
					<mrow>
						\text{Xmin} \amp = -8.5 \amp\amp \text{Xmax} = 15
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						\text{Ymin} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \text{Ymax} = 30
					</mrow>
				</md>
				to verify the graph. In particular, the point <m>(0, 4)</m> lies on the graph. This point tells us that if there is no wind, Francine can fly <m>60</m> miles in <m>4</m> hours, as we calculated earlier.</p>
				<p>
				<figure xml:id="fig-graph-time-against-headwind"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-graph-time-against-headwind"  width="50%"><description>graph showing time to complete trip vs speed of headwind</description></image></figure>
			</p>
			<p>
				The graph is increasing, as indicated by the table of values. In fact, as the speed of the wind gets close to <m>15</m> miles per hour, Francine's flying time becomes extremely large. In theory, if the wind speed were exactly <m>15</m> miles per hour, Francine would never complete her flight. On the graph, the time becomes infinite at <m>x = 15</m>.
			</p>
			<p>
				What about negative values for <m>x</m>? If we interpret a negative headwind as a tailwind, Francine's flying time should decrease for negative <m>x</m>-values. For example, if <m>x = -5</m>, there is a tailwind of <m>5</m> miles per hour, so Francine's effective speed is <m>20</m>  miles per hour, and she can complete the flight in <m>3</m> hours. As the tailwind gets stronger (that is, as we move farther to the left in the <m>x</m>-direction), Francine's flying time continues to decrease, and the graph approaches the <m>x</m>-axis.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>

<p>
	The vertical dashed line at <m>x=15</m> on the graph of <m>t=\dfrac{60}{15-x}</m> is a <term>vertical asymptote</term><idx>vertical asymptote</idx> for the graph. We first encountered asymptotes in <xref ref="basic-functions" text="type-global"/> when we studied the graph of <m>y=\dfrac{1}{x}</m>. Locating the vertical asymptotes of a rational function is an important part of determining the shape of the graph.
</p>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		Queueing theory is used to predict your waiting time in a line, or queue. For example, suppose the attendant at a toll booth can process <m>6</m> vehicles per minute. The average total time spent by a motorist negotiating the toll booth depends on the rate, <m>r</m>, at which vehicles arrive, according to the formula
		<me>
			T=g(r)=\frac{12-r}{12(6-r)}
		</me>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				What is the average time spent at the toll booth if vehicles arrive at a rate of <m>3</m> vehicles per minute?
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Graph the function on the domain <m>[0, 6]</m>.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				What is the vertical asymptote of the graph? What does it tell you about the queue?
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
	<li><p><m>0.25</m> min</p></li>
	<li><p><image source="images/fig-in-ex-ans-7-4-1"  width="80%"><description>rational function</description></image> </p></li>
	<li><p><m>r=7</m>. The wait time becomes infinite as the arrival rate approaches <m>6</m> vehicles per minute.</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

<example>
	<p>
		EarthCare decides to sell T-shirts to raise money. The company makes an initial investment of $100 to pay for the design of the T-shirt and to set up the printing process. After that, the T-shirts cost $5 each for labor and materials.
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				Express the average cost per T-shirt as a function of the number of T-shirts EarthCare produces.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Make a table of values for the function.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Graph the function and explain what it tells you about the cost of the T-shirts.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				If EarthCare produces <m>x</m> T-shirts, the total costs will be <m>100 + 5x</m> dollars. To find the average cost per T-shirt, we divide the total cost by the number of T-shirts produced, to get
				<me>
					C = g(x) = \frac{100 + 5x}{x}
				</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				 We evaluate the function for several values of <m>x</m>, as shown in the table</p><p>
				 <sidebyside><tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
			        <row bottom="minor">
			            <cell><m>x</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>5</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>10</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>20</m></cell>
			        </row>
			        <row>
			            <cell><m>C</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>105</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>55</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>40</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>25</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>15</m></cell>
			            <cell><m>10</m></cell>
			        </row>
			    </tabular></sidebyside>
				If EarthCare makes only one T-shirt, its cost is $105. But if more than one T-shirt is made, the cost of the original $100 investment is distributed among them. For example, the average cost per T-shirt for <m>\alert{2}</m> T-shirts is
				<me>
					\frac{100 + 5(\alert{2})}{\alert{2}}=55
				</me>
				and the average cost for <m>\alert{5}</m> T-shirts is
				<me>
					\frac{100 + 5(\alert{5})}{\alert{5}}=25
				</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				The graph is shown in <xref ref="fig-average-cost" text="type-global"/>. You can use your calculator with the window 
				<md>
					<mrow>
						\text{Xmin} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \text{Xmax} = 470
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						\text{Ymin} \amp = 0 \amp\amp \text{Ymax} = 30
					</mrow>
				</md>
				to verify the graph. Use the <em>Trace</em> to locate on the graph several points from the table of values. For example, the point <m>(5, 25)</m> indicates that if EarthCare makes <m>5</m> T-shirts, the cost per shirt is <m>\$25</m>.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="fig-average-cost"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-average-cost"  width="50%"><description>graph of average cost of production</description></image></figure>
			<p>
				The graph shows that as the number of T-shirts increases, the average cost per shirt continues to decrease, but not as rapidly as at first. Eventually the average cost levels off and approaches $5 per T-shirt. For example, if EarthCare produces <m>\alert{400}</m> T-shirts, the average cost per shirt is 
				<me>
					\frac{100+5(\alert{400})}{\alert{400}}=5.25
				</me>
			</p>
			</li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</solution></example>

<p>
	The horizontal line <m>C = 5</m> on the graph of <m>C = \displaystyle{\frac{100 + 5x}{x}}</m> is a <term>horizontal asymptote</term><idx>horizontal asymptote</idx>. As <m>x</m> increases, the graph approaches the line <m>C = 5</m> but never actually meets it. The average price per T-shirt will always be slightly more than $5. Horizontal asymptotes are also important in sketching the graphs of rational functions.
</p>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		Delbert prepares a <m>20\%</m> glucose solution of by mixing <m>2</m> mL of glucose with <m>8</m> mL of water. If he adds <m>x</m> ml of glucose to the solution, its concentration is given by
		<me>
			C(x) = \frac{2 + x}{8+x}
		</me>
		<ol>
			<li label="a"><p>
				How many milliliters of glucose should Delbert add to increase the concentration to <m>50\%</m>?
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Graph the function on the domain <m>[0, 100]</m>.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				What is the horizontal asymptote of the graph? What does it tell you about the solution?
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
	<li><p><m>4</m> ml</p></li>
	<li><p><image source="images/fig-in-ex-ans-7-4-2"  width="80%"><description>rational function</description></image> </p></li>
	<li><p><m>C=1</m>. As Delbert adds more glucose to the mixture, its concentration increases toward <m>100\%</m>.</p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>
</introduction>
<subsection><title>Domain of a Rational Function</title>
<p>
	Most applications of rational functions have restricted domains, that is, they make sense for only a subset of the real numbers on the <m>x</m>-axis. Consequently, only a portion of the graph is useful for analyzing the application. However, a knowledge of the general shape and properties of the whole graph can be very helpful in understanding a rational function.
</p>
<p>
	As we stated earlier, a rational function is a quotient of two polynomials. Some examples of rational functions are shown below.
	<md>
		<mrow>
			f(x)\amp=\frac{2}{(x-3)^2}\amp\amp\amp g(x)\amp=\frac{x}{x+1}
		</mrow>
		<mrow>
			h(x)\amp=\frac{2x^2}{x^2+4}\amp\amp\amp k(x)\amp=\frac{x^2-1}{x^2-9}
		</mrow>
	</md>
	Because we cannot divide by zero, a rational function <m>f(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{P(x)}{Q(x)}}</m> is undefined for any value <m>x = a</m> where <m>Q(a) = 0</m>. These <m>x</m>-values are not in the domain of the function.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Find the domains of the rational functions <m>f</m>, <m>g</m>, <m>h</m>, and <m>k</m> defined above.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		The domain of <m>f</m> is the set of all real numbers except <m>3</m>, because the denominator, <m>(x - 3)^2</m>, equals <m>0</m> when <m>x = 3</m>.</p>
		<p> The domain of <m>g</m> is the set of all real numbers except <m>-1</m>, because <m>x + 1</m> equals zero when <m>x=-1</m>.</p>
		<p> The denominator of the function <m>h</m>, <m>x^2 + 4</m>, is never equal to zero, so the domain of <m>h</m> is all the real numbers.</p>
		<p> The domain of <m>k</m> is the set of all real numbers except <m>3</m> and <m>-3</m>, because <m>x^2 - 9</m> equals <m>0</m> when <m>x = 3</m> or <m>x = -3</m>.
	</p>
</solution></example>

<note><p>
	We only need to exclude the zeros of the <em>denominator</em> from the domain of a rational function. We do not exclude the zeros of the numerator. In fact, the zeros of the numerator include the zeros of the rational function itself, because a fraction is equal to <m>0</m> when its numerator is <m>0</m> but its denominator is not <m>0</m>.
</p></note>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				Find the domain of <m>F(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x - 2}{x + 4}}</m>.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Find the zeros of <m>F(x)</m>.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol label="a" cols="2">
	<li><p><m>a\ne -4</m></p></li>
	<li><p><m>x=2</m></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Vertical Asymptotes</title>
<p>
	As we saw in <xref ref="Graphing-Polynomial-Functions" text="type-global"/>, a polynomial function is defined for all values of <m>x</m>, and its graph is a smooth curve without any breaks or holes. The graph of a rational function, on the other hand, will have breaks or holes at those <m>x</m>-values where it is undefined.
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		Investigate the graph of <m>f(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{2}{(x - 3)^2}}</m> near <m>x = 3</m>.
	</p>
<solution><p>
	This function is undefined for <m>x = 3</m>, so there is no point on the graph with <m>x</m>-coordinate <m>3</m>. However, we can make a table of values for other values of <m>x</m>. Plotting the ordered pairs in the table results in the points shown in <xref ref="fig-points-near-vertical-asymptote" text="type-global"/>.
	<sidebyside widths="50% 42%" valigns="middle top">
	<tabular top="major" halign="center" right="minor" left="minor" bottom="minor">
        <row bottom="minor">
            <cell><m>x</m></cell>
            <cell><m>y</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>0</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\dfrac{2}{9}</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>1</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\dfrac{1}{2}</m></cell>
        </row>
         <row>
            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>3</m></cell>
            <cell>undefined</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
            <cell><m>2</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>4</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\dfrac{1}{2}</m></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
            <cell><m>6</m></cell>
            <cell><m>\dfrac{2}{9}</m></cell>
        </row>
   </tabular>
	<figure valign="middle" xml:id="fig-points-near-vertical-asymptote"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-points-near-vertical-asymptote"  width="80%"><description>graph showing 6 points about a vertical asymptote</description></image> </figure></sidebyside>

	Next, we make a table showing x-values close to <m>3</m>, as in <xref ref="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function" text="type-global"/>a. As we choose <m>x</m>-values closer and closer to <m>3</m>, <m>(x - 3)^2</m> gets closer to <m>0</m>, so the fraction <m>\dfrac{2}{(x-3)^2}</m> gets very large. This means that the graph approaches, but never touches, the vertical line <m>x=3</m>. In other words, the graph has a vertical asymptote at <m>x=3</m>. We indicate the vertical asymptote by a dashed line, as shown in <xref ref="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function" text="type-global"/>b.
	<figure xml:id="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function"  width="80%"><description>table of values and graph of rational function</description></image> </figure>
</p></solution></example>

<p>
	In general, we have the following result.
</p>
<xi:include href="./assemblage-vertical-asymptotes.xml" />

<note><p>
	If <m>P(a)</m> and <m>Q(a)</m> are both zero, then the graph of the rational function <m>\displaystyle{\frac{P(x)}{Q(x)}}</m> may have a hole at <m>x=a</m> rather than an asymptote. (This possibility is considered in the homework exercises.)
</p></note>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		Find the vertical asymptotes of <m>G(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{4x^2}{x^2 - 4}}</m>.
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><m>x=-2</m> and <m>x=2</m></p></answer>
</exercise>

<p>
	Near a vertical asymptote, the graph of a rational function has one of the four characteristic shapes, illustrated in <xref ref="fig-4-graphs-of-rational-functions" text="type-global"/>. Locating the vertical asymptotes can help us make a quick sketch of a rational function.
</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-4-graphs-of-rational-functions"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-4-graphs-of-rational-functions"  width="70%"><description>4 cases of behavior near vertical asymptote</description></image> </figure>

<example xml:id="example-vertical-asymptote">
	<p>
		Locate the vertical asymptotes and sketch the graph of <m>g(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x}{x + 1}}</m>.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		The denominator, <m>x+1</m>, equals zero when <m>x = -1</m>. Because the numerator does not equal zero when <m>x = -1</m>, there is a vertical asymptote at <m>x = -1</m>. The asymptote separates the graph into two pieces.</p>
		<p> We can use the <term>Table</term> feature of a calculator to evaluate <m>g(x)</m> for several values of <m>x</m> on either side of the asymptote, as shown in <xref ref="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function2" text="type-global"/>a. We plot the points found in this way; then connect the points on either side of the asymptote to obtain the graph shown in <xref ref="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function2" text="type-global"/>b.
	</p>
	<figure xml:id="fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function2"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-table-and-graph-of-rational-function2"  width="80%"><description>table and graph of rational funciton</description></image></figure>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		<ol>
			<li><p>
				Find the vertical asymptotes of <m>f(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{1}{x^2 - 4}}</m> . Locate any <m>x</m>-intercepts.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Evaluate the function at <m>x = -3</m>, <m>-1</m>, <m>1</m>, and <m>3</m>. Sketch a graph of the function.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><ol label="a">
	<li><p><m>x=-2</m> and <m>x=2</m>, no <m>x</m>-intercepts</p></li>
	<li><p><tabular left="minor" right="minor" top="minor" bottom="minor" halign="center">
		<row>
			<cell><m>x</m></cell>
			<cell><m>-3</m></cell>
			<cell><m>-1</m></cell>
			<cell><m>1</m></cell>
			<cell><m>3</m></cell>
		</row>
		<row>
			<cell><m>y</m></cell>
			<cell><m>\frac{1}{5} </m></cell>
			<cell><m>\frac{-1}{3} </m></cell>
			<cell><m>\frac{-1}{3} </m></cell>
			<cell><m>\frac{1}{5} </m></cell>
		</row>
	</tabular>
	<image source="images/fig-in-ex-ans-7-4-5"  width="40%"><description>rational function</description></image></p></li>
</ol></p></answer>
</exercise>

</subsection>



<subsection><title>Horizontal Asymptotes</title>
<p>
	Look again at the graph of <m>g(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x}{x + 1}}</m> in <xref ref="example-vertical-asymptote" text="type-global"/>. As <m>\abs{x}</m> gets large—that is, as we move away from the origin along the <m>x</m>-axis in either direction—the corresponding <m>y</m>-values get closer and closer to <m>1</m>. The graph approaches, but never coincides with, the line <m>y=1</m>. We say that the graph has a <term>horizontal asymptote</term><idx>horizontal asymptote</idx> at <m>y=1</m>.
</p>
<p>
	When does a rational function <m>f(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{P(x)}{Q(x)}}</m> have a horizontal asymptote? It depends on the degrees of the two polynomials <m>P(x)</m> and <m>Q(x)</m>. The degree of the numerator of <m>g(x)= \displaystyle{\frac{x}{x + 1}}</m> is equal to the degree of the denominator. In other words, the highest power of <m>x</m> in the numerator (1, in this case) is the same as the highest power in the denominator.
</p>
<p>
	Consider the three rational functions whose graphs are shown in <xref ref="fig-3-cases-end-behavior" text="type-global"/>.
</p>
<figure xml:id="fig-3-cases-end-behavior"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-3-cases-end-behavior"><description>3 cases of end behavior</description></image> </figure>

<p>
	<ul>
	<li>The graph of <m>r(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x + 1}{x^2}}</m> in <xref ref="fig-3-cases-end-behavior" text="type-global"/>a has a horizontal asymptote at <m>y = 0</m>, the <m>x</m>-axis, because the degree of the denominator is larger than the degree of the numerator. Higher powers of <m>x</m> grow much more rapidly than smaller powers. Thus, for large values of <m>\abs{x}</m>, the denominator is much larger in absolute value than the numerator of <m>r(x)</m>, so the function values approach <m>0</m>.</li>

	<li>The graph of <m>s(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x^2 - 4}{2x^2}}</m> in <xref ref="fig-3-cases-end-behavior" text="type-global"/>b has a horizontal asymptote at <m>y = \dfrac{1}{2}</m>, because the numerator and denominator of the fraction have the same degree. For large values of <m>\abs{x}</m>, the terms of lower degree are negligible compared to the squared terms. As <m>x</m> increases, <m>s(x)</m> is approximately equal to <m>\dfrac{x^2}{2x^2}</m>, or <m>\dfrac{1}{2}</m>. Thus, the function values approach a constant value of <m>\dfrac{1}{2}</m>.</li>

	<li>The graph of <m>t(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x^2 + 1}{x - 1}}</m> in <xref ref="fig-3-cases-end-behavior" text="type-global"/>c does not have a horizontal asymptote, because the degree of the numerator is larger than the degree of the denominator. As <m>\abs{x}</m> increases, <m>x^2 + 1</m> grows much faster than <m>x - 1</m>, so their ratio does not approach a constant value. The function values increase without bound.</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
	We summarize our discussion as follows.
</p>

<xi:include href="./assemblage-horizontal-asymptotes.xml" />

<example>
	<p>
		Locate the horizontal asymptotes and sketch the graph of <m>h(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{2x^2}{x^2 + 4}}</m>.
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		The numerator and denominator of the fraction are both second-degree polynomials, so the graph does have a horizontal asymptote. The lead coefficients of <m>P(x)</m> and <m>Q(x)</m> are <m>2</m> and <m>1</m>, respectively, so the horizontal asymptote is <m>y = \dfrac{2}{1}</m>, or <m>y=2</m>.</p>
		<p> The function <m>h</m> does not have a vertical asymptote because the denominator, <m>x^2 + 4</m>, is never equal to zero.</p>
		<p> The <m>y</m>-intercept of the graph is the point <m>(0, 0)</m>. We can plot several points by evaluating the function at convenient <m>x</m>-values, and use the asymptote to help us sketch the graph, as shown in <xref ref="fig-horizontal-asymptote-above-x-axis" text="type-global"/>.
		<figure xml:id="fig-horizontal-asymptote-above-x-axis"><caption></caption><image source="images/fig-horizontal-asymptote-above-x-axis"  width="60%"><description>rational function with horizontal asymptote at y=2</description></image> </figure>
	</p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		Locate the horizontal and vertical asymptotes and sketch the graph of <m>k(x) = \displaystyle{\frac{x^2 - 1}{x^2 - 9}}</m>. Label the <m>x</m>- and <m>y</m>-intercepts with their coordinates.
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><m>y= 1</m>; <m>x = -3</m>, <m>x = 3</m>
<image source="images/fig-in-ex-ans-7-4-6"  width="35%">
  <description>
    rational function
  </description>
</image> </p></answer>
</exercise>

</subsection>




<subsection><title>Applications</title>
<p>
	It is often useful to simplify the formula for a rational function before using it. (See Algebra Skills Refresher <xref ref="appendix-Working-with-Algebraic-Fractions" text="type-global"/> to review operations on algebraic fractions.)
</p>

<example>
	<p>
		When estimating their travel time, pilots must take into account the prevailing winds. A tailwind adds to the plane's ground speed, while a headwind decreases the ground speed. Skyhigh Airlines is setting up a shuttle service from Dallas to Phoenix, a distance of <m>800</m> miles.
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				Express the time needed for a one-way trip, without wind, as a function of the speed of the plane.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Suppose there is a prevailing wind of <m>30</m> miles per hour blowing from the west. Write expressions for the flying time from Dallas to Phoenix and from Phoenix to Dallas.
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				Write an expression for the round-trip flying time, excluding stops, with a <m>30</m>-mile-per-hour wind from the west, as a function of the plane's speed. Simplify your expression.
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
<solution>
	<p>
		<ol label="a">
			<li><p>
				Recall that <m>\text{time} = \dfrac{\text{distance}}{\text{rate}}</m>. If we let <m>r</m> represent the speed of the plane in still air, then the time required for a one-way trip is
				<me>
					f(r)=\frac{800}{r}
				</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				On the trip from Dallas to Phoenix, the plane encounters a headwind of <m>30</m> miles per hour, so its actual ground speed is <m>r-30</m>. On the return trip, the plane enjoys a tailwind of <m>30</m> miles per hour, so its actual ground speed is <m>r+30</m>. Therefore, the flying times are
				<me>
					\text{Dallas to Phoenix:}\hphantom{blank}\frac{800}{r-30}
				</me>
				and
				<me>
					\text{Phoenix to Dallas:}\hphantom{blank}\frac{800}{r+30}
				</me>
			</p></li>
			<li><p>
				The round-trip flying time from Dallas to Phoenix and back is
				<me>
					F(r ) =\frac{800}{r-30}+\frac{800}{r+30}
				</me>
				The LCD for these fractions is <m>(r - 30)(r + 30)</m>. Thus,
				<md>
					<mrow>
						\frac{800}{r-30}+\frac{800}{r+30} \amp= \frac{800\alert{({r+30})}}{(r-30)\alert{({r+30})}}+\frac{800\blert{({r-30})}}{(r+30)\blert{({r-30})}}
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						\amp = \frac{(800r + 24000) + (800r - 24000)} {(r + 30)(r - 30)}
					</mrow>
					<mrow>
						\amp = \frac{1600r}{r^2 - 900}
					</mrow>
				</md>
			</p></li>
		</ol>
	</p>
	<p>
		(See Algebra Skills Refresher <xref ref="appendix-Working-with-Algebraic-Fractions" text="type-hybrid"/> to review adding fractions.)
	</p>
</solution></example>

<exercise><statement>
	<p>
		Navid took his outboard motorboat 20 miles upstream to a fishing site, returning downstream later that day. His boat travels 10 miles per hour in still water. Write an expression for the time Navid spent traveling, as a function of the speed of the current.
	</p>
</statement>
<answer><p><m>\dfrac{400}{100-x^2} </m> hrs</p></answer>
</exercise>


</subsection>
<xi:include href="./summary-7-4.xml" /> <!-- summary  -->
<xi:include href="./section-7-4-exercises.xml" /> <!-- exercises  -->
</section> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->