<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-5-4" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="2">
		<li><p>Log scale</p></li>
		<li><p>Log-log paper</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>A <term>log scale</term> is useful for plotting values that vary greatly in magnitude. We plot the log of the variable instead of the variable itself.
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			A log scale is a <term>multiplicative scale</term>: Each increment of equal length on the scale indicates that the value is multiplied by an equal amount.
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			The pH value of a substance is defined by the formula
			<me>\text{pH}=-\log_{10}[H^+]</me>
			where <m>[H^+]</m> denotes the concentration of hydrogen ions in the substance.
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			The loudness of a sound is measured in decibels, <m>D</m>, by
			<me>D=10 \log_{10}\left(\frac{I}{10^{-12}}\right)</me> 	where <m>I</m> is the intensity of its sound waves (in watts per square meter).
		</p></li>
    	<li><p>
    		The Richter magnitude, <m>M</m>, of an earthquake is given by
    		<me>M=\log_{10}\left(\frac{A}{A_0} \right)</me>where <m>A</m> is the amplitude of its seismographic trace and <m>A_0</m> is the amplitude of the smallest detectable earthquake.
    	</p></li>
    	<li><p>A <em>difference</em> of <m>K</m> units on a logarithmic scale corresponds to a <em>factor</em> of <m>10^K</m> units in the value of the variable.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>What numbers are used to label the axis on a log scale?</p></li>
		<li><p>What does it mean to say that a log scale is a multiplicative scale?</p></li>
		<li><p>Delbert says that <m>80</m> decibels is twice as loud as <m>40</m> decibels. Is he correct? Why or why not?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which is farther on a log scale, the distance between <m>5</m> and <m>15</m>, or the distance between <m>0.5</m> and <m>1.5</m>?
		</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-5-4-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Plot values on a log scale: <hash />1<ndash/>4, 9 and 10</p></li>
		<li><p>Read values from a log scale: <hash />5<ndash/>8, 11<ndash/>14, 19 and 20</p></li>
		<li><p>Compare values on a log scale: <hash />15<ndash/>18</p></li>
		<li><p>Use log scales in applications: <hash />21<ndash/>40</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->