<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-4-5" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="4">
		<li><p>Doubling time</p></li>
		<li><p>Amortization</p></li>
		<li><p>Half-life</p></li>
		<li><p>Annuity</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>We can use the ratio method to fit an exponential function through two points.</p>
		<xi:include href="./assemblage-exponential-through-2-points.xml" />
		</li>
		<li><p>Every increasing exponential has a fixed <term>doubling time</term>. Every decreasing exponential function has a fixed <term>half-life</term>.</p></li>
		<li><p>If <m>D</m> is the doubling time for a population, its growth law can be written as <m>P(t) = P_0 2^{t/D}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>If <m>H</m> is the half-life for a quantity, its decay law can be written as <m>Q(t) = Q_0(0.5)^{t/H}</m>.</p></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-future-value.xml" /></li>
    	<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-present-value.xml" /></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Compare the methods for fitting a line through two points and fitting an exponential function through two points.</p></li>
		<li><p>
			A population of <m>3</m> million people has a doubling time of <m>15</m> years. What is the population <m>15</m> years from now? <m>30</m> years from now? <m>60</m> years from now?
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			Francine says that because the half-life of radium-223 is <m>11.7</m> days, after <m>23.4</m> days it will have all decayed. Is she correct? Why or why not?
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			Which is larger: the sum of all the deposits you make into your retirement fund, or the future value of the fund? Why?
		</p></li>
		<li><p>
			Which is larger: the sum of all the payments you make towards your mortgage, or the amount of the loan? Why?
		</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-4-5-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Fit an exponential function through two points: <hash />1<ndash/>18</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the doubling time or half-life: <hash />19<ndash/>26</p></li>
		<li><p>Write an exponential function, given the doubling time or half-life: <hash />27<ndash/>34, <hash />39<ndash/>42</p></li>
		<li><p>Use the formula for future value of an annuity: <hash />43 and 44</p></li>
		<li><p>Use the formula for present value of an annuity: <hash />45 and 46</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->