<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-6-4" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Maximum value</p></li>
		<li><p>Minimum value</p></li>
		<li><p>Vertex form</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Quadratic models may arise as the product of two variables.</p></li>
		<li><p>The maximum or minimum of a quadratic function occurs at the vertex.</p></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-vertex-form-of-quadratic.xml" /></li>
		<li><p>We can convert a quadratic equation to vertex form by completing the square.</p></li>
		<li><p>We can graph a quadratic equation in vertex form using transformations.</p></li>
		<li><p>A <m>2\times 2</m> system involving quadratic equations may have one, two, or no solutions.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>How can you tell whether a variable given by a quadratic equation has a maximum value or a minimum value?</p></li>
		<li><p>What is wrong with this statement: The maximum or minimum value given by a quadratic equation is the average of the <m>x</m>-intercepts?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain why <m>-4</m> is the smallest function value for <m>f (x) = 2(x - 3)^2 - 4</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>In the equation <m>y = \dfrac{1}{3}(x + 5)^2 - 2</m>, what does each of the constants tell you about the graph?</p></li>
		<li><p>Francine attempts to write the equation <m>g(x) = 2x^2 - 6x + 1</m> in vertex form as follows: <m>g(x) = (2x^2 - 6x +\alert{9}) + 1 - \alert{9}</m>. What is wrong with her work?</p></li>
		<li><p>Without doing any calculations, solve the system <m>y = x^2 + 4, y = 2 - 3x^2</m>. (<em>Hint</em>: Visualize the graphs.)</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-6-4-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Find the maximum or minimum value of a quadratic function: <hash />1<ndash/>14</p></li>
		<li><p>Convert a quadratic equation from vertex form to standard form: <hash />19<ndash/>22</p></li>
		<li><p>Convert a quadratic equation from standard form to vertex form: <hash />23<ndash/>28</p></li>
		<li><p>Use transformations to graph a quadratic equation: <hash />15<ndash/>28</p></li>
		<li><p>USolve a system involving quadratic equations: <hash />31<ndash/>50</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->