<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-2-4" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Increasing</p></li>
		<li><p>Decreasing</p></li>
		<li><p>Concave up</p></li>
		<li><p>Concave down</p></li>
		<li><p>Empirical model</p></li>
		<li><p>Mechanistic model</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="*1*">
		<li><p>The shape of a graph describes how the output variable changes.</p></li>
		<li><p>A nonlinear graph may be concave up or concave down. If a graph is concave up, its slope is increasing. If it is concave down, its slope is decreasing.</p></li>
		<li><p>The basic functions can be used to model physical situations.</p></li>
		<li><p>Some situations can be modeled by piecewise functions</p></li>
		<li><p>Fitting a curve to the data is not enough to produce a useful model; appropriate scientific principles should also be considered.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="*1*">
		<li><p>Sketch the graph of a function whose slope is positive and increasing.</p></li>
		<li><p>Sketch the graph of a function whose slope is positive and decreasing.</p></li>
		<li><p>Which basic function is increasing but bending downward?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which basic function is decreasing but bending upward?</p></li>
		<li><p>Why is it bad practice to choose a model purely on the shape of the data plot?</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-2-4-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol>
		<li><p>Sketch a graph whose shape models a situation: <hash />1<ndash />18</p></li>
		<li><p>Choose one of the basic graphs to fit a situation or a set of data: <hash />19<ndash />24, 35<ndash />44</p></li>
		<li><p>Decide whether the graph of a function is increasing or decreasing, concave up or concave down from a table of values: <hash />25<ndash />28</p></li>
		<li><p>Write and sketch a piecewise define function to model a situation: <hash />45<ndash />48</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->