<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-8-1" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Linear system</p></li>
		<li><p>Solution of a system</p></li>
		<li><p>Intersection point</p></li>
		<li><p>Equilibrium point</p></li>
		<li><p>Dependent</p></li>
		<li><p>Inconsistent</p></li>
		<li><p>Consistent and independent</p></li>
		<li><p>Demand equation</p></li>
		<li><p>Supply equation</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>We can solve a <m>2\times 2</m> linear system by graphing. The solution is the intersection point of the two graphs.</p></li>
		<li><p>A linear system may be <term>inconsistent</term> (has no solution), <term>dependent</term> (has infinitely many solutions), or <term>consistent and independent</term> (has one solution).</p></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-inconsistent-and-dependent-systems.xml" /></li>
		<li><p>We can use a system of equations to solve problems involving two unknown quantities.</p></li>
		<li><p>In economics, the price at which the <term>supply</term> and <term>demand</term> are equal is called the <term>equilibrium price</term>.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>How can you test whether <m>(a, b)</m> is a solution to a system of two linear equations?</p></li>
		<li><p>Do two lines always intersect in one point? Explain.</p></li>
		<li><p>When is a system useful for solving an applied problem?</p></li>
		<li><p>Name two algebraic methods for solving a <m>2\times 2</m> linear system.</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the result of performing elimination on a dependent system?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain the terms <term>demand function</term>, <term>supply function</term>, and <term>equilibrium price</term>.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-8-1-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Solve a <m>2\times</m> linear system by graphing: <hash />1<ndash/>14, 31<ndash/>34</p></li>
		<li><p>Identify inconsistent and dependent systems: <hash />15<ndash/>20</p></li>
		<li><p>Write a system of two linear equations to solve a problem: <hash />21<ndash/>30</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 
</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->