<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-7-2" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Degree</p></li>
		<li><p>Multiplicity</p></li>
		<li><p>Inflection point</p></li>
		<li><p>Quartic</p></li>
		<li><p>Turning point</p></li>
		<li><p>Cubic</p></li>
		<li><p>Corollary</p></li>
		<li><p>Zero</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>The graphs of all polynomials are smooth curves without breaks or holes.</p></li>
		<li><p>The graph of a polynomial of degree <m>n</m> (with positive leading coefficient) has the same long-term behavior as the power function of the same degree.</p></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-factor-theorem.xml" /></li>
		<li><p>A polynomial of degree <m>n</m> can have at most <m>n</m> <m>x</m>-intercepts.</p></li>
		<li><p>At a zero of multiplicity two, the graph of a polynomial has a turning point. At a zero of multiplicity three, the graph of a polynomial has an inflection point.</p></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Describe the graphs of polynomials of degrees <m>0</m>, <m>1</m>, and <m>2</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>What does the degree of a polynomial tell you about its long-term behavior?</p></li>
		<li><p>What is a zero of a polynomial?</p></li>
		<li><p>How are zeros related to the factors of a polynomial?</p></li>
		<li><p>What do the zeros tell you about the graph of a polynomial?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain the difference between a turning point and an inflection point.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-7-2-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Identify <m>x</m>-intercepts, turning points, and inflection points: <hash />1<ndash/>8, 11<ndash/>18</p></li>
		<li><p>Use a graph to factor a polynomial: <hash />21<ndash/>28</p></li>
		<li><p>Sketch the graph of a polynomial: <hash />29<ndash/>46</p></li>
		<li><p>Find a possible formula for a polynomial whose graph is shown: <hash />47<ndash/>52</p></li>
		<li><p>Graph translations of polynomials: <hash />53<ndash/>56</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 
</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->