<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-5-1" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Inverse function</p></li>
		<li><p>Horizontal line test</p></li>
		<li><p>One-to-one</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>The <term>inverse</term> of a function describes the same relationship between two variables but interchanges the roles of the input and output.
		</p></li><p></p>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-inverse-functions.xml" /></li>
		<li><p>We can make a table of values for the inverse function, <m>f^{-1}</m>, by interchanging the columns of a table for <m>f</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>If a function is defined by a formula in the form <m>y = f (x)</m>, we can find a formula for its inverse function by solving the equation for <m>x</m> to get <m>x = f^{-1}(y)</m>.</p></li>
    	<li><p>The inverse function <m>f^{-1}</m> undoes the effect of the function <m>f</m>, that is, if we apply the inverse function to the output of <m>f</m>, we return to the original input value.</p></li>
    	<li><p>If <m>f^{-1}</m> is the inverse function for <m>f</m>, then <m>f</m> is also the inverse function for <m>f^{-1}</m>.</p></li>
    	<li><p>The graphs of <m>f</m> and its inverse function are <term>symmetric about the line <m>y = x</m></term> .</p></li>
    	<li><p><term>Horizontal line test</term>: If no horizontal line intersects the graph of a function more than once, then the inverse is also a function.</p></li>
    	<li><p>A function that passes the horizontal line test is called <term>one-to-one</term>.</p></li>
    	<li><p>The inverse of a function <m>f</m> is also a function if and only if <m>f</m> is one-to-one.</p></li>
    	<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-functions-and-inverse-functions.xml" /></li>
    	<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-domain-and-range-of-the-inverse-function.xml" /></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Explain how the terms <term>inverse function</term>, <term>one-to-one</term>, and <term>horizontal line test</term> are related.</p></li>
		<li><p>If you know that <m>f^{-1}(3) = -7</m>, what can you say about the values of <m>f</m> ?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain how to use a graph of the function <m>g</m> to evaluate <m>g^{-1}(2)</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Evaluate <m>f ( f^{-1}(5))</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>Delbert says that if <m>f (x) = x^{3/5}</m>, then <m>f^{-1}(x) = x^{-3/5}</m>. Is he correct? Why or why not?</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-5-1-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Given certain function values, find values of the inverse function: <hash />1<ndash/>4</p></li>
		<li><p>Interpret values of the inverse function: <hash />5<ndash/>12</p></li>
		<li><p>Find a formula for the inverse function: <hash />9<ndash/>22, 27<ndsh/>34</p></li>
		<li><p>Graph the inverse function: <hash />15 and 16, 23<ndash/>34</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the domain and range of the inverse function: <hash />33 and 34</p></li>
		<li><p>Use the horizontal line test to identify one-to-one functions: <hash />35<ndash/>42</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->