<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-1-5" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Slope-intercept form</p></li>
		<li><p>Point-slope form</p></li>
		<li><p>Parameter</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Linear functions form a two-parameter family, <m>f (x) = b + mx</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>The initial value of a linear function and the <m>y</m>-intercept of its graph are given by <m>b</m>. The rate of change of the function and the slope of its graph are given by <m>m</m>.</p></li>
		<li><p>The slope-intercept form, <m>y = b + mx</m>, is useful when we know the initial value and the rate of change.</p></li>
		<li><p>The point-slope form, <m>y = y_1 + m(x - x_1)</m>, is useful when we know the rate of change and one point on the line.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>How can you put a linear equation into slope-intercept form?</p></li>
		<li><p>What do the coefficients in the slope-intercept form tell you about the line?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain how to graph a line using the slope-intercept method.</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain how to find an equation for a line from its graph.</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain how to use the point-slope form for a linear equation.</p></li>
		<li><p>Francine says that the slope of the line <m>y = 4x - 6</m> is <m>4x</m>. Is she correct? Explain your answer</p></li>
		<li><p>Delbert says that the slope of the line <m>3x - 4y = 8</m> is <m>3</m>. Is he correct? Explain your answer.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-1-5-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Write a linear equation in slope-intercept form: <hash />1<ndash />14</p></li>
		<li><p>Identify the slope and <m>y</m>-intercept: <hash />1<ndash />10</p></li>
		<li><p>Graph a line by the slope-intercept method: <hash />11<ndash />14</p></li>
		<li><p>Find a linear equation from its graph: <hash />21<ndash />26, 29–32, 53<ndash />56</p></li>
		<li><p>Interpret the slope and <m>y</m>-intercept: <hash />21<ndash />28, 63 and 64</p></li>
		<li><p>Find a linear equation from one point and the slope: <hash />33<ndash />50</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->