<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-6-3" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Vertex</p></li>
		<li><p>Conjugate pair</p></li>
		<li><p>Axis of symmetry</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>The graph of a quadratic function <m>f (x) = ax^2 + bx + c</m> is called a <term>parabola</term>. The values of the constants <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> determine the location and orientation of the parabola.</p></li>
		<li><p>For the graph of <m>y = ax^2 + bx + c</m>, the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the <term>vertex</term> is <m>x_v = \frac{-b}{2a}</m>. To find the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the vertex, we substitute <m>x_v</m> into the formula for the parabola.</p></li>
		<li><p>The graph of the quadratic function <m>y = ax^2 + bx + c</m> may have two, one, or no <m>x</m>-intercepts, according to the number of distinct real-valued solutions of the equation <m>ax^2 + bx + c = 0</m>.</p></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-discriminant.xml" /></li>
		<li><xi:include href="./assemblage-graph-general-quadratic.xml" /></li>
    </ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Sketch a parabola that opens downward. Show the location of the <m>x</m>-intercepts, the <m>y</m>-intercept, the vertex, and the axis of symmetry.</p></li>
		<li><p>Describe how the value of <m>a</m> in <m>y = ax^2</m> alters the graph of the basic parabola.</p></li>
		<li><p>Describe how the value of <m>c</m> in <m>y = x^2 + c</m> alters the graph of the basic parabola.</p></li>
		<li><p>Suppose you know that the <m>x</m>-intercepts of a parabola are <m>(-8, 0)</m> and <m>(2, 0)</m>. What is the equation of the parabola's axis of symmetry?</p></li>
		<li><p>State a formula for the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the vertex of a parabola. How can you find the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the vertex?</p></li>
		<li><p>Suppose that a given parabola has only one <m>x</m>-intercept. What can you say about the vertex of the parabola?</p></li>
		<li><p>Explain why a quadratic equation has one (repeated) solution if its discriminant is zero, and none if the discriminant is negative.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-6-3-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Graph transformations of the basic parabola: <hash />1 and 2, 7, and 8</p></li>
		<li><p>Locate the <m>x</m>-intercepts of a parabola: <hash />3<ndash/>6</p></li>
		<li><p>Locate the vertex of a parabola: <hash />3<ndash/>6, 13, and 14</p></li>
		<li><p>Sketch the graph of a quadratic function: <hash />15<ndash/>24, 41, and 42</p></li>
		<li><p>Use the discriminant to describe the solutions of a quadratic equation: <hash />25<ndash/>40</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->