<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- <mathbook><book> -->

<subsection xml:id="summary-2-6" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Section Summary</title>
<subsubsection><title>Vocabulary</title>
<p>
	Look up the definitions of new terms in the Glossary.
	<ul cols="3">
		<li><p>Domain</p></li>
		<li><p>Range</p></li>
		<li><p>Restricted domain</p></li>
	</ul>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>CONCEPTS</title>
<p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>The <term>domain</term> of a function is the set of permissible values for the input variable.</p></li>
		<li><p>The <term>range</term> is the set of function values (that is, values of the output variable) that correspond to the domain values.</p></li>
		<li><p>A relationship between two variables is a <term>function</term> if each element of the domain is paired with only one element of the range.</p></li>
		<li><p>We can identify the domain and range of a function from its graph. The domain is the set of <m>x</m>-values of all points on the graph, and the range is the set of <m>y</m>-values.</p></li>
		<li><p>If the domain of a function is not given as part of its definition, we assume that the domain is as large as possible.</p></li>
		<li><p>In applications, we may restrict the domain and range of a function to suit the situation at hand.</p></li>
	</ol>
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>STUDY QUESTIONS</title><p>
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Explain how to find the domain and range of a function from its graph.</p></li>
		<li><p>What is the domain of the function <m>f (x) = 4</m>? What is its range?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which of the eight basic functions are increasing on their entire domain? Which are decreasing on their entire domain?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which of the eight basic functions are concave up on their entire domain? Which are concave down on their entire domain?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which of the eight basic functions can be evaluated at any real number? Which can take on any real number as a function value?</p></li>
		<li><p>Which of the eight basic functions can be graphed in one piece, without lifting the pencil from the paper?</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection><title>SKILLS</title><p>
	Practice each skill in the <xref ref="section-2-6-exercises" text="global">Homework</xref> problems listed.
	<ol label="1">
		<li><p>Find the domain and range of a function from its graph: <hash />1<ndash />16</p></li>
		<li><p>Restrict the domain of a function to suit an application: <hash />17<ndash />24</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the domain of a function from its algebraic formula: <hash />25<ndash />30</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the corresponding domain value for a given range value: <hash />31<ndash />38</p></li>
		<li><p>Find the range of a function on a given domain: <hash />39<ndash />50</p></li>
	</ol>
</p></subsubsection> 

</subsection>
<!-- </appendix> -->
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->